<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Righteous judgment placed upon the heads of malicious opposers and persecuting apostates in some brief animadversions upon Francis Buggs book, entitled, De Christiana libertate, in which his great weakness and gross wickedness is detected, his foul defamations and uncivil reflections are reprehended : with a seasonable warning to him and the rest of his abettors in their mischievous work of opposition to and separation from, the Lord and his people / by a lover of peace, Robert Sandilands : together with an Ingredient by another hand.</title>
            <author>Sandilands, Robert.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 184 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 71 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62156</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S661</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32326</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12638391</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12638391</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64952</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62156)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64952)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1535:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Righteous judgment placed upon the heads of malicious opposers and persecuting apostates in some brief animadversions upon Francis Buggs book, entitled, De Christiana libertate, in which his great weakness and gross wickedness is detected, his foul defamations and uncivil reflections are reprehended : with a seasonable warning to him and the rest of his abettors in their mischievous work of opposition to and separation from, the Lord and his people / by a lover of peace, Robert Sandilands : together with an Ingredient by another hand.</title>
                  <author>Sandilands, Robert.</author>
                  <author>Richardson, Richard, 1623?-1689. Another ingredient against the venom in F.B.'s book.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15], 135 [i.e. 123], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Bringhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Another ingredient in F.B.'s book" (p. 127-1359) has caption title and signature at end: Richard Richardson.</note>
                  <note>Manuscript notes on back fly-leaf; ms. signature "Rebecca Bury" verso t.p.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, with print show-through and loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bugg, Francis, 1640-1724? --  De Christiana libertate.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:64952:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Advertiſement</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THere is now in the PRESS a Book, Entituled,</hi> The Liberty of an Apoſtate Conſcience: being a plain Narrative of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie long depending Between <hi>Francis Bugg</hi> on the one part, and <hi>Samuel Cater</hi> and <hi>George Smith</hi> on the other part: whereby <hi>F. Bugg's Liberty of Conſcience</hi> is proved not only <hi>Unchriſtian,</hi> but <hi>Immoral</hi> and <hi>Injurious.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64952:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Righteous Judgment</hi> Placed upon the Heads of Malicious OPPOSERS AND Perſecuting Apoſtates: In ſome brief Animadverſions upon <hi>Francis Buggs</hi> Book, entituled, <hi>De Chriſtiana Libertate:</hi> In which his great Weakneſs and groſs Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is Detected, his foul Defamations and unci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Reflections are Reprehended. With a ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Warning to him and the reſt of his Abettors in their Miſchievous Work of <hi>Oppoſition</hi> to and <hi>Separation</hi> from the Lord and his People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Lover of Peace,</hi> Robert Sandilands.</p>
            <p>Together with an <hi>Ingredient</hi> by another hand.</p>
            <q>Now I beſeech you Brethren, mark them which cauſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions and Offences, contrary to the Doctrine which ye have learned, and avoid them,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 16.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>For there are many <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nruly and Vain Talkers, whoſe Mouthes muſt be ſtopped,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Tit 1.10, 11.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>I will remember his Deeds, Prating againſt us with Mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Words,
<bibl>
                  <hi>3 John</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Bringharſt,</hi> at the Sign of the Book in <hi>Grace-Church-ſtreet.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:64952:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64952:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ALthough this, with divers other Teſtimonies, may prove as Water ſpilt on the ground, and ſeem altogether as ineffectual, ſo as to produce any real convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon the Spirits of ſome of our Oppoſers, who are become many of them ſo obſtinate, ſtout and hard-hearted, that the moſt clear demonſtration that may be produced to convince them of their folly, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears partly impoſſible to prevail, ſo as to perſwade or bring them to a true ſenſe of their <hi>unchriſtian proceedings</hi> and <hi>malicious endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours:</hi> Yet I am not without hope, but the ſober unbyaſſed perſons, whoſe minds are not pre-poſſeſſed, neither with <hi>partial ſelfiſh deſigns
<pb facs="tcp:64952:3"/>of Intereſt,</hi> on the one hand; nor with <hi>private Affection,</hi> on the other hand; may reap of the profit, and gain a right underſtanding by their ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous peruſal and deliberate exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of this and other Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</p>
            <p>And therefore is it mainly for ſuch we are incouraged to open, and give a true naked relation of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as plainly before the All-ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Heart-ſearching, Divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, <hi>Who will bring all the hidden things of diſhoneſty to Light;</hi> and indeed, had it not been upon this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, I do reckon that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, rambling, impertinent ſtuff, made up with moſt notorious lyes and malicious Inſinuations, grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Slanders and Reflections, were not worth while to take notice of; for I mind well the ſaying of a Wiſe Man, <hi>Contra verboſos noli contende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re verbis; <hi>We are not to conteſt by words againſt windy Men,</hi>
               </hi> or <hi>Men of words;</hi> and he gives a good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>Sermo datur cunctis animi ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientia
<pb facs="tcp:64952:3"/>paucis: <hi>Many have the Gift of Speech, but few</hi>
               </hi> (comparatively) <hi>attain to Wiſdom,</hi> and therefore we are adviſed in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>Anſwer not a Fool in his Folly, leſt thou become like unto him:</hi> But leſt advantage ſhould be catched, the ſimple enſnared, and the true Enquirers miſinformed, we are not willing to be quite ſilent.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Reader</hi> may alſo take notice what dreadful hardneſs of Heart ſome of theſe contrary oppoſite Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are fallen under, that they have had the daring boldneſs moſt inſolently to deny the very power of God in its Operations and Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, when it hath wrought upon his people true tenderneſs and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs of Heart; and if they have thus impudently ſlighted the ſame, no wonder then that they ſo baſely abuſe us at ſuch a rate as <hi>W. R. T. C.</hi> and this <hi>F. B.</hi> and others have done.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Reader,</hi> if ſo be that through he good hand of God, thou art not
<pb facs="tcp:64952:4"/>one tinctured with this dirty foul prophane flouting, and I may ſay in ſome reſpect, Blaſphemous and Atheiſtical Spirit. O! praiſe it highly, I beſeech thee, as thy great mercy, as I do; and I pray God keep thee with my ſelf and all Gods faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful honeſt-hearted people, from the Snares of this murdering Spirit, that hath deſtroyed in ſuch in whom it hath prevailed, the inward ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſenſe of the precious life of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, that they have as openly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied and violently oppoſed the ſame as any of our former or preſent publick E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies among the Profeſſors ever did or can do.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſ.</hi> Crying out, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with our inward ſenſe, away with our diſcerning of Spirit, which I have heard ſome of them to ſay.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And if <hi>(Reader)</hi> thou be one of a mild, ſober, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired mind, and deſires not to be much concerned with theſe Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies; then Ladviſe thee, regard well the proſperity of the work of Truth, and feel thy daily experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence thereof in thy own particular,
<pb facs="tcp:64952:4"/>(and Oh! well had it been this day with many, <hi>That they had looked more at home than abroad.</hi>) Beware I pray thee of a <hi>cold, luke-warm, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different Spirit</hi> (which would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear <hi>neutral,</hi> and it is <hi>not,</hi> but is neerer to that which is wrong than right) and this I know lies neer to enter many well-diſpoſed perſons, who are of a good natural temper, and mean well; and if it happen thou be at any time exerciſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the differences of Opinions, or in things in themſelves indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, be not ſtiff in maintaining thy own Judgment of them; but rather be of a condeſcending mind, and ſo let thy humility and meekneſs appear thereby, that thou art ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther willing to acquieſce in thy Sentiments, to the underſtanding and ſenſe of others (when eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) there is a reaſon and a cauſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the ſame) then ſeem to be of ſuch who are heady, high, and ſelf-conceited in their own imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations; there is a notable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion
<pb facs="tcp:64952:5"/>of a certain Devout Perſon wort by of obſervation; <q>Its true (ſaith he) that every one willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inclines to follow thoſe who are of the ſame Opinion with him.</q> 
               <hi>Sedſi Deus eſt intra nos <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eceſſe eſt ut re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquamus etiam quandoque noſtrum ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire propter bonum pacis;</hi> i. e. <hi>But if God be amongſt us, there is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity that we ſometimes alſo for the good of Peace forſake or leave our own</hi> Opinion; <hi>for who is he that is ſo Wiſe that can fully know all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if ſo be thou art one that hath ſuffered thy Affections to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt thy Judgment and cloud thy <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, that thou cannot diſcerne nor judge of things clearly as they are on neither ſides, and yet ſome true tenderneſs and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will to both, and a reverend regard to the Teſtimony of Truth remaining in thy heart. Well <hi>Reader;</hi> I would counſel thee in the firſt place be ſtill, patient and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et in thy mind, and then draw in
<pb facs="tcp:64952:5"/>the Affections of thy Soul from all viſible preſentations, and ſo ſingly wait upon God, to feel him reveal that to thee which thou ſees not; and in the interim have a ſpecial care, that <hi>hardneſs of heart</hi> inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly come not over thee, and ſteal in upon thee, as too many have been thus ſadly betrayed, eſpecially after once that their Affections have been catched with that tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming, cunning, and alluring Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Envy and Diſcord: For, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis later in herba.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, <hi>Reader,</hi> I would by way of Caution premoniſh and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat thee, not to entertain harſh thoughts of me, when thou reads ſome Expreſſions that may ſeem ſomewhat hard, and thereby judge I want <hi>Charity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I can uprightly ſay in the ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my heart, and do in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the allſeeing great God, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genouſly profeſs, That what I here wrote in this following Teſtimony, proceeds not from any kind of pieque,
<pb facs="tcp:64952:6"/>prejudice or envy to the perſons of any of theſe contrary party, being both altogether a ſtranger to this <hi>Francis Bugg;</hi> having no occaſion to entertain any ſuch thing, nor no temptation as upon an outward account, to lead me thereunto; and alſo being of another Nation: and truly it was contrary to my diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, having no delight or ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction (for my life is not in theſe Controverſies and Contentions) to have meddled at all with them to appear thus in publick; but <hi>F. B</hi>'s Book coming to my hand, beyond either what I was in the leaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting or deſirous of; and after my peruſal of the ſame, I found a <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Zeal</hi> and <hi>Indignation</hi> ariſe in me againſt that moſt malicious mocking Spirit of the Author: and I could not but ſhew an Abſolute Antipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and utter Abhorrency of that baſe ſcurrilous abuſive Spirit, that hath prevailed upon ſuch as are Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents to this proud conceited man, to vent forth ſo many lying Inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb facs="tcp:64952:6"/>uncivil and unchriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections, abominable Forgeries and Defamations, as well againſt the whole Body of Friends in this and other Nations, as againſt divers particular honeſt Friends, <hi>viz. G. F. G. W. R. R. I. F,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And I can ſay, Bleſſed be the Lord, as for my ſelf, ſo for many of his Servants, that what we have given forth as the ſentence and judgment of Truth againſt this diſorderly, looſe, libertine Spirit, and ſuch as walk therein, is in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure from the ſame Good-will, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and tender regard to the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Well-being of the Souls of our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Detractors, as appeared in our bleſſed Head, the <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> in whom there was no <hi>Spleen, Bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> or <hi>Envy,</hi> againſt the Perſons of thoſe Hypocrites, the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſes,</hi> in his time, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he denounced ſuch and ſuch dreadful <hi>Woes</hi> unto them.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Reader,</hi> there are divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſſages I could have taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
<pb facs="tcp:64952:7"/>of, which I have omitted (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſomewhat ſtraitned at preſent with the conveniency of leaſure, and engaged in another ſervice, more delightſome to me) as concerning the lamentable <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> and <hi>Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlidings</hi> of theſe <hi>Separates,</hi> vho are but wheeling round about again in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their old Center; ſo that indeed I may ſay the Scale is turned, and the Scene is changed with them, and thoſe things which formerly they teſtified against they are found in the practice of, building again the things which they once deſtroyed, thereby making themſelves Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors, as divers inſtances could be produced; but theſe two or three may ſerve as a ſufficient proof at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I know divers of them, have fallen back from the pure Scriptural language of <hi>Thou</hi> to one (which Friends of Truth in our day have been led into by the Spirit of the Lord, and in obedience there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, continue in the ſame) into the
<pb facs="tcp:64952:7"/>corrupt Babyloniſh Speech as <hi>You</hi> to one perſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> They have degenerated from their Teſtimony, and fallen in again with the World in their Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the <hi>heatheniſh Names</hi> of the <hi>Months,</hi> as this <hi>F. B.</hi> parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly ſays, page <hi>206. <hi>Being in</hi> London <hi>in the Month of February.</hi>
               </hi> And,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Their woful Apoſtatizing from their antient Teſtimony, as to <hi>paying of Tythes,</hi> and <hi>going to the Prieſts to be marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>T.</hi> C's. 2d. Part <hi>Bab.</hi> builders, p. 5. and 4 Part p 9. where he ſaith ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, <hi>It is his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple to do ſo and ſo.</hi>
               </note> both as well pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed as profeſſed to be <hi>T. C's.</hi> Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, juſtifying the ſame.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Reader,</hi> for thy further ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, I refer thee to read that Book called, <hi>The Accuſer of the Brethren caſt out,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Tho. Elwoods Antidote againſt the Infection of</hi> W. Rs. <hi>Book,</hi> lately printed, of ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial ſervice, wherein his, and the reſt of his Brethren in Miſchief,
<pb facs="tcp:64952:8"/>their Confuſions and Contradictions are plainly diſcovered, and the charge of Apoſtacy and Innovation is juſtly retorted upon them.</p>
            <p>Finally, <hi>Reader,</hi> I leave thee to the ſerious peruſal of this inſuing Treatiſe, and deſire that it may be in the holy Fear of Almighty God, and with a calm, moderate, and impartial mind; and ſo recommend thee to the word of his ſaving Grace, which alone can open to thee both the Myſtery of Godlineſs and alſo of Iniquity, that thou may duly attend and obey what it teacheth, and ſo thereby thou may attain to the one, and eſcape the other, is the end of this labour of Love through him, who is a real Well-wiſher of all the Sons and Daughters of men,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. S.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London</hi> 
                  <date>the 12th of the 5 Mo. 1682.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:64952:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>THE INTRODUCTION:</head>
               <p>THat Exerciſe which through Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Aſſiſtance I am now about, in undertaking to diſcover the Helliſh Enmity, and moſt malicious, bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, venemous Spirit of <hi>Deceit</hi> and <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord,</hi> that hath poſſeſſed and prevailed upon too too many of thoſe (with hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy ſadneſs of Heart and great grief of Soul do I expreſs it) whoſe minds are Adulterated from the Experimental liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Senſe of the Holy-Divine Gift of God: As it is truly in the Croſs to my own will or natural Inclination, who would have more gladly been contented to be ſilent in ſuch a work; ſo was it very contrary to my expectations, when it pleaſed the Almighty God of Heaven and Earth firſt to draw me forth into the Service and Labour of his bleſſed Truth, of ever being concerned with ſuch hard and grievous Exerciſes amongſt falſe Brethren; occaſioned by the ſubtle Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems of the old Troubler of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in his wicked Agents, what by their
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64952:9"/>unchriſtian and inhumane Reflection<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whereby I might be liable to the Cenſure of the Civil Powers,<note place="margin">Obs. I was more than once reproached by them as a Jeſuit, of which many Witneſſes I could produce.</note> and what by their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainful; uncivil beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour other ways, that for my part they have fully evidenced to me (though outwardly Strangers to moſt of them) to be in the firſt place perſons altogether void of the living Vertue, Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; and Efficacy of the Truth and true Religion, and ſo far from being <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in Nature</hi> and <hi>Poſſeſſion,</hi> however, under the bare Name and empty Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof.</p>
               <p>The ſecond place deſtitute of that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Diſcretion, Prudence and Civility as amongſt Men, and ſo far from the Reaſon or Rational Principle in Man; whereby that ſaying is verified, <hi>Man that is in honour, and underſtandeth not, is like the Beaſts, that periſh;</hi> Pſal. 40<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 20.</p>
               <p>But what ſhall I ſay! hath not this been always the lot and the very portion of the Righteous in all Generations under e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>every Diſpenſation,<note place="margin">As there was a <hi>Cain</hi> againſt an <hi>Abel,</hi> an <hi>Iſhmael</hi> againſt an <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac,</hi> a <hi>Eſau</hi> againſt <hi>Iacob,</hi> and a <hi>Judas</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Chriſts Diſciples.</note> from the beginning of the Creation, ſince the Lord gather'd a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64952:9"/>to himſelf, to this our Day or Age, thus to be attended with various deep Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes by <hi>Oppoſitions, Violence</hi> and <hi>Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions</hi> from the World on the one hand, and by <hi>Diſtraction, Diſcord</hi> and <hi>Separation</hi> on the other hand, of thoſe who have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared as amongſt us, but were not of us; and therefore that they might be made manifeſt what Bottom and Evil Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit they were of, notwithſtanding they lurked under, and were cover'd for a time with a Profeſſion of the Way and Holy Truth of God, they have gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from us, as the Apoſtle writ con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Antichriſts, <hi>They went out from us, but they were not of us:</hi> and the Reaſon he gives is clear, <hi>For</hi> (ſays he) <hi>if they had been of us, they would, no doubt have continued with us: But they went out,</hi> (to what end?) <hi>That they might be made manifeſt, that they were not all of us,</hi> 1 John 2.19. We may obſerve, the Church of Chriſt in his time was then ſadly troubled with theſe Antichriſts, ſuch as roſe up in Appearance for Chriſt againſt Chriſt, in oppoſing the Bleſſed Divine Manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his Spirit, through the Members of his Church: And I remember, he makes particular mention of one <hi>Diotrephes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> who it ſeems (as many like unto him in our day following his very foot-ſteps)
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64952:10"/>Ioved to have the preheminence, and who prated againſt them with malicious Words; and good <hi>Paul,</hi> was he not very ſenſible in fore-ſeeing that this would at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Churches, and therefore fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned them thereof in his farewel to the Elders of <hi>Epheſus? Take heed therefore unto your ſelves, and to all the Flock, over the which the Holy Ghoſt hath made you O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeers; for I know this, that after my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting, ſhall grievous Wolves (under the form or appearance its like of Lambs) not ſparing the Flock: alſo of your own ſelves ſhall Men ariſe, ſpeaking perverſe things, to draw away Diſciples after them,</hi> Acts 20.25, 26, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And in his Salutation to the <hi>Romans,</hi> Chap. 16. v. 17. ſaith, <hi>Now I beſeech you, Brethren, mark them which cauſe <hi>Diviſions <hi>and</hi> Offences,</hi> contrary to the Doctrine which you have learned, and avoid them.</hi> So that we may clearly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, it is no new or ſtrange thing that hath happened to be our ſad Exerciſe; as indeed I do look upon it to be the moſt grievous of all the Exerciſes that could have befallen us, I mean as with reſpect of the Body of Friends.</p>
               <p>And now amongſt many of the chief Agents of Cruelty, Slander and Envy, whom the Devil (that great Enemy to the Peace of Chriſts Church) hath made
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64952:10"/>uſe of, and this pernicious work of oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to, and ſeperation from the good Order and wholeſome Diſcipline thereof, I find lately one called <hi>Francis Bugg</hi> in <hi>Aragon,</hi> a proud ſelf-conceited perſon, and yet as confuſed and malicious as any, which I hope (anon) to Evince, by ſome brief <hi>Animadverſions on the Second Part of his Book,</hi> called, <hi>De Chriſtiana Libertate;</hi> the firſt part only relating to <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> none of his Work, but by a nameleſs Author.</p>
               <p>So far now as I feel my ſelf concern'd for the Truths ſake, and the vindication thereof, to give forth my Teſtimony as well againſt the great weakneſs, as the groſs wickedneſs of this Helliſh, dark piece of deceitful work of Envy and Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and to detect his groundleſs Sugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings, unchriſtian Reflections and unci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Informations, not at all deſigning thereby to undertake the Anſwering of every particular paſſage that hath relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to particular perſons ingaged in the differences betwixt our Friends, and the ſeparate party (for that would be a work both more tedious, and alſo would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire more pains then at preſent I can take to undertake the ſame) which I leave to them as they find themſelves concerned, in Truth to take notice of; my preſent
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64952:11"/>work then only is to make ſome ſhor Obſervations of that which in General I am concerned with, and lies moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious in my view.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Righteous Judgment placed upon the Heads of our Malicious Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>HAving peruſed the <hi>Second Part</hi> of <hi>Francis Bugg</hi>'s Book, he miſcalls, <hi>De Chriſtiana Libertate,</hi> I do not ſo much as find any one page or paſſage to have the leaſt reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of,<note place="margin">I doubt very much whether he knows what the true Chrsſtian liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty means</note> or Relation to <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> in a true and proper ſenſe; I mean what he has wrote himſelf, and not what is Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed from other Authors, abſtracting which, there will be but a ſmall parcel of his remaining.</p>
               <p>Beſides, thou may take notice of the <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Self-conceitedneſs</hi> of this vain Man, who gives his Book a <hi>Latin</hi> Title, which ſignifies no more in <hi>Latin</hi> then in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64952:11"/>
                  <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and has no more Emphaſis nor Authority in it, therefore only uſeful for <hi>Vain Oſtentation:</hi> eſpecially conſidering that the Book it ſelf is no ways correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the Title.</p>
               <p>In his Epiſtle, page 4. He alledges two principal Reaſons, why we look upon him and his Adherents to be <hi>no Quakers,</hi> or conſequently as he ſays <hi>no Chriſtians.</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> He ſays, <hi>Our Non-ſubmiſſion and Non-conformity to the New Order of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
                  </q> (He begins thus in his flouting Airy mind.) <q>
                     <hi>And Secondly, That their way of compelling and Antichriſtian way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding to bring to, and force <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity, is by us ſlighted and contemn'd.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer,</hi> But we know right well, there is a <hi>Third</hi> and a more weighty Reaſon than either of theſe, and that is, <hi>We have a certain inward ſenſe and ſure diſcerning from the Infallible Spirit of Truth</hi> (which I know they will not regard, or admit of) <hi>that the wrong, wicked, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Spirit hath entered into them, and thereby are Adulterated in theſe minds from the bleſſed pure Spirit of Chriſt Ieſus, and departed from the Truth in the inward parts, whereby they are degenerated, and were ſo in their Spirits, before ever they durſt publickly appear in this treacherous
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64952:12"/>work of Separation, and before it wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſo notorious as it is now.</hi> And ſo they having Apoſtatized from the Truth, and the living Vertue and ſenſible Operation and Experience of the Life thereof, firſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in their own particulars, thus, <hi>They</hi> (and not <hi>We</hi>) have rendred themſelves <hi>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Quakers, or no Chriſtians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For we never concluded any perſon to be <hi>truly a Chriſtian</hi> ſimply becauſe of his outward Conformity to the Profeſſion of Truth, and becauſe of his Submiſſion to the Holy and Decent Order of Chriſts Church, in reſpect there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing viſible can rightly conſtitute and properly denominate any Man or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>True Chriſtians</hi> in the ſight of God, who regards more the inward bent, frame and diſpoſition of the Minds of People, than their outward appearance, however glorious it may be; and therefore it is of abſolute neceſſity that their hearts and ſpirits be uprightly ſtated in his ſight, if ever they attain to the Nature of true Chriſtianity.</p>
               <p>Now though it be confeſt, that many <hi>outwardly</hi> may appear in the view of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for a time ſeemingly <hi>ſtrict</hi> and <hi>ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> in their <hi>Converſations,</hi> ſo that nothing can be juſtly charged againſt them, that is apparently <hi>Wicked</hi> and <hi>Groſs;</hi> yet in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64952:12"/>the mean time their <hi>Hearts not right,</hi> nor <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ound before the Lord,</hi> ſomething that is <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bominable, offenſive</hi> and <hi>grievous</hi> to his <hi>Holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pirit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Thus hath it been with many of the ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate party.</note> is ſecretly lodg'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd privately enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ain'd, as their <hi>beloved Delila,</hi> which at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſt (may be) breaks forth into ſome Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancy or other; I ſay one (as a <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite</hi>) may be thus dreſſed up with a ſpecious ſhew and fair cover, appear ſo and ſo; Yea, and for their intereſt ſake Conform to that which is good and praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, and which in its ſelf is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable and laudible; but in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom rotten and deceitful; yet though theſe do ſo, it will not follow in good reaſon, that thoſe who are truly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly ſanctified, cleanſed and purified in their Conſcience from dead works, and whoſe Hearts are Sincere, Honeſt, and Upright, ſhould not ſo and ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear as to the outward, in an holy harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Life and innocent Converſation, and alſo in a Conformity and Submiſſion to that which is Orderly and Decent, and to be ſubject to follow that which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, needful and profitable, amongſt a People, no more then that's true; though as the common Proverb is, <hi>It is not all Gold that gliſters.</hi> And as we
<pb facs="tcp:64952:13"/>ſay, <hi>All are not in the Poſſeſſion of what they are in the Profeſſion of.</hi> Yet is there no true Gold that gliſters? And ſurely thoſe who do poſſeſs of the living Vertue of Truth, and are faithful to the Lord, they are ingaged publickly to appear in <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of, and <hi>Confeſſion</hi> to the ſame.</p>
               <p>In the beginning of the Preface, <hi>page</hi> 7, <hi>F. B.</hi> ſays, <hi>The main thing intended by this Diſcourſe is to ſhew the Miſchief of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions on tender Conſciences in matters Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Thus he inſinuates as a falſe charge up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the whole Body of our Friends to be guilty of, which indeed is their main principal Baſis or ground, from whence doth proceed all their fierce violent Claſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, bitter and malicious Invectives, baſe and unchriſtian Reflections, <hi>viz.</hi> Their Imaginary, formed, and ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſuppoſition and envious ſuſpicion, <hi>That we endeavoured to compel and force tender Conſciences in matters Spiritual, to be conform'd and in ſubjection to that, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the perſwaſion of their minds, and Light of Chriſt in their Conſciences;</hi> this is eaſily diſprov'd, and has been fully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed by many living Teſtimonies that we have given forth on this account, both by word and writing, and for a further confirmation thereof, thus do I affirm
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64952:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>on the behalf of all my dear Friends, who are thus abuſed by theſe foul, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, and ſcoffing Spirits, <hi>That the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, the ſearcher of Hearts, and tryer of Reins, he knows we never endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured nor deſigned to compel any to ſubject in a Conformity to that which we know was both juſt and reaſonable, who were not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfied in their own Conſciences, and not freedom and clearneſs in their minds thereto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For they who received Truth in the love thereof, and continue in ſubjection to it, the power and force of it will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and make them willing to obey the voice of God, immediately in their own Hearts, and in the Mouths of his Servants; which Voice of God calls un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Holineſs, without <hi>which none ſhall ſee him,</hi> and there being an aptneſs or prone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in many after they are reached to by the Lord to neglect that Duty he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of them, therefore in his tender Love, hath <hi>he given Gifts for the work of the Miniſtry, for the perfecting of the Saints, for the Edifying of the Body, till we all come in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Faith into a perfect Man, unto the meaſure of his Stature, of the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt, Eph.</hi> 4.8. &amp;c. — And well ſaid the Apoſtle <hi>Peter, Yea I think it meet as long as I am in this Tabernacle to ſtir you
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64952:14"/>up</hi> (or) <hi>to ſtir up your pure minds by way of remembrance) that we may be mindful of the words which were ſpoken before by the Holy Prophets, and of the Commandement of us the Apoſtles of the Lord and Saviour; knowing this firſt, that there ſhall come in the laſt days ſcoffers, walking after their own Luſts,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.15.3.1, 2. &amp;c. Which alſo was practiſed by the Apoſtles in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, Admonition, Counſel, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, and Condemnation, as the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Truth Directed them, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſeveral ſtates of People, to whom they Miniſtered by Word or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Reader,</hi> it is well known, that any who were really ſcrupulous, from a true tenderneſs of their Spirits; careful, or fearful to do any thing but what they found to be their Duty, and in the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, did ſee they were called to be obedient to the ſame; over theſe we have been very tender, and have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged and counſelled them, <hi>Singlely to wait upon the Lord, for a ſight and ſenſe from him by the in ſhinings of his pure Light of that which they ought to do,</hi> and if we could inform their underſtandings, and in the good hand of the Lord be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental to clear their Judgments, by open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them the profit and great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64952:14"/>reaped by thoſe who have found it their place to be in Unity with their Brethren in a <hi>Chriſtian Condeſcention,</hi> to thoſe things that are decent, orderly, and profitable in the Church of Chriſt, that we have endeavoured to do, and (bleſſed be the Lord) our labour of Love and pains therein hath proved ſucceſsful, and many have been helped thereby, to ſee through the Myſterious wiles and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle workings of the Enemy, both imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately and inſtrumentally.</p>
               <p>So thou mayſt be aſſured, we never pleaded for a conformity or ſubmiſſion of any to the Chriſtian Order, and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Diſcipline amongſt us, but as they came to be <hi>Convinced in their own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,</hi> and <hi>well perſwaded in themſelves</hi> from a clear and ſenſible Conviction, <hi>That it was their bounden duty ſo to do.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſay, and thou mayſt ſee, that this Authors falſe Charge, with all the reſt of his confederacy, in all their lying Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, proceed from a <hi>baſe perverſe Spirit</hi> (that does ſurmiſe to People that we were <hi>bringing in an implicit Faith and blind Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, by forcing a Conformity before Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction;</hi> which is oppoſed by us, with our utmoſt endeavours) and is of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, the Father of lyes, who is the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Author of all this miſchievous dark
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64952:15"/>work of <hi>Separation,</hi> &amp;c. and makes uſe of thoſe his wicked Agents to defend the ſame, under the ſpecious pretence of <hi>Liberty of Conſcience, Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience;</hi> and influences them to defame the Lords faithful and innocent Servants, by malicious, abuſive Reflections, and falſe Inſinuations, to amuſe People, as if the end of all their labours and travels in the Service of Truth, for the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Gods Heritage, were to bring them into a <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> of <hi>ſuch</hi> and <hi>ſuch Canons, Decrees,</hi> and <hi>Orders,</hi> that tended to an <hi>Apoſtacy, Impoſition,</hi> and what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot.</p>
               <p>Now, I hope, <hi>Reader,</hi> thou wilt plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee, that the very main thing intended by this angry Author, as the principal foundation of his work, is notorious falſe, and abominable; ſeeing it is ſo, without all doubt, then thou mayſt ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conclude all the reſt of his work (I mean, his enſuing Treatiſe) is a piece of perfect <hi>Forgery,</hi> abſolute deſigned <hi>Lyes</hi> and <hi>Slanders,</hi> ſo much of it as inſinuates and has a tendency to introduce a falſe report, and beget a wrong belief concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us, whoſe Innocency is well known both in the ſight of God and ſober-mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed people, that it was never our buſineſs directly or indirectly, to drive any to a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64952:15"/>forced ſubjection contrary to their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion &amp; inclination of their own minds. And for my part, I do ingeniouſly declare, that I could never perceive any ſuch thing leſs or more amongſt Friends where ever I have been in any of our Meetings, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther truly do I yet ſee (and I hope never ſhall, I deſire never to ſee it whilſt I live) that by all the vain Scribling, Prating, and Tattling of their Idle, Ridiculous Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, either by Words or Books of our Oppoſers, that they have produced any convincing ſolid proof, rational or clear demonſtration to any judicious under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Perſons, that the Body of Friends are ſo and ſo Apoſtatized, and do ſo and ſo drive, impoſe, force and compel any to a Conformity to the wholeſome Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian proceedings in their Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Meetings, or that <hi>G. F.</hi> that faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Servant of the Lord, is become an <hi>Apoſtate</hi> or <hi>Innovator,</hi> as <hi>W. R.</hi> &amp;c. moſt maliciouſly ſuggeſts.</p>
               <p>As for this of <hi>F. B</hi>'s I have conſidered it, and I find much <hi>weakneſs,</hi> attended with a great deal both of extream <hi>Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and alſo of fooliſh <hi>Drollery, Malice,</hi> and <hi>Envy,</hi> and I doubt not but the impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial, and ſuch as are not prepoſſeſſed with prejudice, will eaſily diſcern and readily obſerve the ſame by what follows.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:64952:16"/>
               <p>For in Page 8. he brings in an imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent parallel, ſaying, <hi>And now I will ſhew you a Parallel betwixt the Treatment, which the Proteſtants met withal from the hands of the</hi> Papiſts <hi>for their pains, and betwixt the Treatment</hi> W. R. T. C. <hi>and others have met withal from the hands of</hi> G. F. <hi>and thoſe of party with him for their pains;</hi> and ſo ſets down at large in <hi>page</hi> 11, 12, 13. the manner of the Papiſts Curſing <hi>Thomas Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net,</hi> for publiſhing and manifeſting their Error.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Is not here the height of Malice and extream wickedneſs? <hi>firſt</hi> to inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate moſt falſly our being like to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, for which <hi>F. B.</hi> thou deſerves a dreadful reward, and ſhall unavoidably meet with it from the hand of the juſt God of Heaven and Earth, if thou ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repent not.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Secondly,</hi> To compare what ſeveral of us have given forth from the Spirit of the Lord, in a true living Zeal, and from a holy Conſtraint and Deteſtation againſt that rending, tearing, and dividing Spirit, that is curſed of God for ever; which weighty Teſtimonies through his People ſhall ſtand over thy head, and all thoſe joyned with thee in that miſchievous work of <hi>Separation from the Lord,</hi> and <hi>Oppoſition to his Work,</hi> and that which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64952:16"/>would <hi>divide</hi> and <hi>ſcatter his Heritage:</hi> I ſay, to bring in Parallel, betwixt what the Lord gives forth in the Authority of his Eternal power, through his Children either ſingly, as with reſpect of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; or joyntly, as a Body of People gathered together by his power, to give forth a true Sentence and Judgment upon that which is wrong, with what the <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Papiſts</hi> have done in their dark and blind minds, by their <hi>Bulls</hi> and <hi>Curſes.</hi> Oh! what a wicked and abominable thing is this!</p>
               <p>And as if this was not ſufficient to ſhew thy Rage, thou alſo baſely inſinuates, <hi>page</hi> 15. As if <hi>we were not a ſuffering Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>our ſelves,</hi> and had but once the Law to aſſiſt us, in our Church Cenſures,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>We would expoſe People to <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Faggot, Curſe</hi> and <hi>Excommunicate</hi> them, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive them of their <hi>Priviledges</hi> and <hi>Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, Temporal,</hi> as well as <hi>Spiritual,</hi> as ever the <hi>Papiſts</hi> did:</hi> And that Reader, this is the true <hi>Engliſh</hi> and natural Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of this Mans unſuitable Parallel, and not by bare Inferences there-from, he expreſſes the ſame more fully in plain le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible Characters, falſly ſaying, <hi>page</hi> 200. <hi>A Man may tranſgreſs the Scriptures, days without number, but yet never be Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated by</hi> G. F. <hi>and his Party</hi> (this is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64952:17"/>largly inſerted, but not at all proved in his Book) <hi>but <hi>I. B.</hi> never ſold but one Book, namely that of</hi> W. R. <hi>his publiſhing that ever I heard of</hi> (but I ask how many did <hi>I. B.</hi> vend and diſpoſe of them into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try? and I doubt he ſold many more then one, which I believe himſelf will not deny) <hi>And ſo you ſee he is diſmembred, no Spiritual Followſhip, no ſpiritual Communion they can have with him</hi> (that's true, nor with thee either, or any ſuch Rambling, Ranting, Looſe, Libertine Spirits, like <hi>W. R.</hi> and thy ſelf, yet here <hi>no Curſe,</hi> though <hi>no Concord,</hi> no deprivation of <hi>Temporal Priviledges,</hi> though an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of <hi>Spiritual Communion</hi>) — Nay, (ſays <hi>F. B.</hi>) <hi>they do not only teſtifie againſt that <hi>Bad Spirit,</hi> as they account it, but <hi>him alſo,</hi>
                  </hi> viz. <hi>the <hi>Man alſo.</hi> Oh that we could but ſay, <hi>Take him Iaylor,</hi>
                  </hi> and that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually; and further as a compleat Draught of thy Divelliſh Malice in <hi>page</hi> 203. where thou ſays, <hi>Had I all the Books of Controverſie by me, I preſume it were a thing too hard for me to undertake, ſo that I muſt take a ſtep into the Papiſts Road of Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clty and Severity,</hi> &amp;c. Oh! the moſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, Cruel, Hard-hearted Man, full of Malice and Miſchief, what ſhall I ſay unto thee? Certainly the Lord God will call thee to an account for this perverſe,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64952:17"/>deceitful, devilliſh piece of Treachery, Lies, and implacable Enmity: and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member I tell thee, in the fear of the great God, if thou do not deeply lament for, unfeignedly and ſpeedily repent of it, moſt dreadful ſhall thy Portion be, and moſt terrible ſhall the Judgment and Indignation be, which thou muſt feel from the hand of the Righteous Judge of Heaven and Earth.</p>
               <p>Being much aſtoniſhed to ſee the great boldneſs and ſtrange Impudence of this unruly Perſon, and other Rambling, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly, Oppoſite Spirits, that dare give forth in Print, and publickly alſo report ſuch manifeſt Forgeries, Notorious and Apparent Calumnies againſt the Faithful Innocent people of the Lord, and in the ſerious conſideration of all their ungodly Railing Expreſſions, with many ſcurrilous Mockings, abuſive and ſcoffing Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. May not I ſay, and many alſo with me, as they of old expreſſed their Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of that unuſual paſſage mentioned in <hi>Judges</hi> 19. <hi>And it was ſo, that all that ſaw it, ſaid, <hi>There was no ſuch deed done nor ſeen, from the day that the Children of</hi>
                  </hi> Iſrael <hi>came up out of the Land of</hi> Egypt <hi>unto this day.</hi> Conſider of it, take Advice, and ſpeak your minds, Was there ever ſuch Wickedneſs and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64952:18"/>Folly done? Was there ever ſuch Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Envy ſeen in any People (ſince the time the Lord appeared unto us, and brought us from under the <hi>Egyptian Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage</hi> and <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> and ſince the day that the Lord Viſited us by his mighty Hand, and out-ſtretched Arm, and gathered us to be a People to himſelf) as in theſe now, who <hi>under the Profeſſion of the ſame Truth,</hi> have (it ſeems) even made a Covenant with Hell, Death and the Devil, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed a Confederacy together, to War againſt the Lord and his People, by their open Oppoſition to, and diſdainful ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the comely and commendable Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices in the Church of Chriſt; eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidering (which greatly aggravates their guilt) the ſingular advantages they have had above many people, what un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding I believe divers of them came unto, concerning the work of Truth, their great knowledg they had attained of the Principles of the true Religion, and ſome of them (its like) once enjoyed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimental nearneſs to the Lord, and Fellowſhip with him and his People; and yet for ſuch to become as Abſolute, Stour, Reſolute Enemies, to oppoſe both, as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verany, yea by many degrees are farworſe, and as it were in the ſuperlative endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to exceed their former Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64952:18"/>(<hi>I</hi> mean the old dry Apoſtates) was there ever ſuch a deed done or ſeen? And that notwithſtanding the Lord hath been ſo graciouſly pleaſed, both ſignally to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by his Heavenly and Divine power, as well for the preſervation as the vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of his choſen faithful ones, who have ſtood in his Counſel, and in the uprightneſs of their Hearts could appeal their Innocency to him, and alſo hath evidently manifeſted, and apparently diſcovered his Wrath and fierce Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt his and their Enemies on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very hand, in ſo much that thoſe who in their time roſe up with a high, lofty and imperious Mind, proud and exalted Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, abuſing and villiſying the Innocent Servants of the Lord amongſt whom our ancient faithful Friend <hi>G. F.</hi> has not been one of the leaſt concern'd both then and at this preſent juncture of Controverſie; I ſay, where are theſe now, with all their confuſed ſtuff of Janglings and Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? What came all their Noiſes and Buſtlings to? We clearly ſee the Devil and all his curſed Agents could not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce what they deſigned thereby; and why? The Lord <hi>Iehova,</hi> the mighty God of Heaven and Earth appeared as a terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Enemy againſt them.</p>
               <p>Now <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Admiration to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64952:19"/>me; to ſee thee treading on in the very Foot-ſtepts of thoſe old Back-ſliders from the Holy Commandment of Life deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them, who from the ſame perverſe Spirit, to the ſame end, and much after the ſame method <hi>Oppoſed the Truth, and abuſed Friends thereof; as thou doſt:</hi> but thou and <hi>W. R.</hi> &amp;c. go ſome ſteps be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond them, and did not they (as well as thou <hi>F. B.</hi>) print divers Scandalous Pamphlets, amongſt which there was one called, <hi>Liberty of Conſcience aſſerted againſt Impoſition</hi> (if I be not much mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken) wherein they endeavoured to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſent Friends to the World as <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates</hi> and <hi>Innovators,</hi> and ſuch as were ſetting up a <hi>Romiſh Hierarchy,</hi> and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Arbitrary Juriſdiction over tender Conſciences? ſo that now its clear as the Sun ſhines, their falſe charge thou and thy Adherents have revived, their way you have followed, their Cauſe you have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken, evidently demonſtrates you to be in the ſame work of wickedneſs, and one with theſe in the very root of bitterneſs.</p>
               <p>How comes it <hi>Francis</hi> that thou art ſo benumbed, ſtupified, hardned and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed, yea and befooled by the Devil. But alaſs! What ſhall I ſay,. He, eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the God of this Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d hath lulled thee
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64952:19"/>into a deep Lethargy or ſleep, and ſo blinded thy Eyes again (if ever they were once opened) that thou, and ſuch as thou art, cannot ſee nor apprehend what you are running and hurrying head-long into, till the Flames of Eternal Judgment, and the fury of that fiery Indignation make you ſenſible what your wicked devilliſh Work has been.</p>
               <p>But O! the earneſt Prayer of my Soul, is to the God of infinite Mercy, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable Compaſſions, <hi>That you may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent ſuch an awakning, and that you in time now may be rouſed up and allarm'd by his Righteous Judgments in your Hearts, by ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under the ſame, and by bowing to the Indignation of the Almighty, you may obtain mercy from him to your poor Immortal ſouls, before the day of mercy be quite ſhut againſt you; that though you then may cry, yet you will not be heard.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>IN p. 21. I find <hi>F. B.</hi> ſay, <hi>But if</hi> G. F. <hi>and his party ſhall ſtifly ſtand to it, that the womens meetings it of Divine Inſtitution,</hi> &amp;c. and then brings in an impertinent, need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Query, <hi>Whether Chriſt was deficient ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64952:20"/>in his Delivering to that honoured Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory or in his Memory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſay he was in neither; but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Capacities of the People, amongſt whom he converſed, it was that he ſpoke, delivered, and opened things to them: And <hi>F. B.</hi> ſcoffingly interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates, <hi>And who did he constitute in his room to ſupply that defect, whether a viſible head, namely</hi> G. F. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>We do know very well whom he did appoint in his room, when he was to be removed bodily; he encouraged his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples with a ſweet promiſe, <hi>I will not leave you comfortleſs but the Comforter, which is the Holy Ghoſt, whom the Father will ſend in my Name,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> The true force of the <hi>Greek</hi> word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, is <hi>Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate,</hi> one called to, ſent for, invited to come, upon what oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions or for what end ſoever, ſee 1 <hi>John</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>he ſhall teach you, and bring all things to your remembrance, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I have ſaid unto you:</hi> and although he gave forth and ſpoke much unto them, yet they were not able to bear all things, therefore he ſays, <hi>I have yet many things to ſay unto you, but you cannot bear them now; howbeit, when the Spirit of Truth is come, he will guide you into all Truth; for he will not ſpeak of himſelf, but whatſoever he ſhall hear, that ſhall he ſpeak, and he
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64952:20"/>will ſhew you things to come; he ſhall receive of mins, and ſhall ſhew it unto you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From which we may obſerve, that there is large room left for the Spirit of Truth (who ſhould receive of Chriſt's and ſhew unto his followers to inſtruct and lead to, never contrary, but agreeable with the Scriptures of Truth, that which is needful, proper, and profitable in the Church; for the preſervation of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof, in the comely commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble goſpel of Order, that thereby the lovely ſweet Unity, Concord and Heavenly Harmony may be retained amongſt them, to their mutual joy, comfort, and edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to the praiſe of his glory, who hath called us to be his peculiar people, zealous of good works, and hath preſerved us againſt the malice, violence and rage of the Devil and all his Inſtruments, under every appearance or transformation.</p>
               <p>Now whereas this angry peeviſh Man makes ſuch a noiſe againſt and buſtlings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>Lawfulneſs</hi> of <hi>Womens Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> becauſe <hi>he cannot find Chapter and verſe expreſly ſet down in the Scripture for erecting Womens Meetings diſtinct from the Men, to be conſtantly ſet up once a month about the</hi> 10th <hi>houre of the day.</hi> This he brings in (pag. 101, 102.) as in the name of the Profeſſors; but I look upon it rather as
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64952:21"/>his than theirs, and therefore ſhall apply my ſelf particularly to him in what follows upon this Subject.</p>
               <p>Tell me now <hi>F. Bugg.</hi> honeſtly (if there be the leaſt dram of Ingenuity yet remaining with thee) haſt not thou in thy time per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed divers lawful, and may be (with reſpect to thy particular ſatisfaction) very neceſſary Duties, and that upon a Religious account too, and ſuch as thou couldſt not well omit without offending the Lord, or breaking thy peace with him; and yet if thou wert to be queſtioned by the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors (for that hath been always then great plea againſt us) to produce expreſly Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Chap. and verſe to prove the Lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thereof: if thou haſt not, I am ſure I have, and many have found it as a pleaſure upon our Spirits, being commanded of the Lord to go about ſuch and ſuch a ſervice (I could name many particulare) for which we could not give expreſs Scripture to prove the lawfulneſs of the ſame. Pray what Chap. and verſe from any of ther Four Evangeliſts can I give to any of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours that would ask the ſame of me, Suppoſe I were commanded of the Lord to go to ſuch or ſuch a Steeple-houſe in City or Countrey, or it were weighty up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my Sprit to viſit any one particular Meeting or County in this Nation: this
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64952:21"/>I hope thou wilt not deny but its in the firſt place lawful for me ſo to do; and in the ſecond place neceſſary alſo, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Command of God, which I am bound to obſerve, as duly as if it were ſet down in Scripture expreſly. R. S. <hi>I command thee to go to ſuch a place, at ſuch a day, in ſuch an hour,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And next <hi>F. B.</hi> where will thou find ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly Chap. and Verſe in the Scriptures that thou ſhould meet in ſuch a place on the Firſt day or Week day, at ſuch an hour, either for Mens Meetings to take care of the Poor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or other Solemn Meetings, on the Account of Gods Worſhip?</p>
               <p>And further, to come cloſer to the Matter, if Profeſſors ſhould Query of thee, <hi>Come</hi> F. B. <hi>give us Chap. and Verſe expreſly: to prove thy Practice of keeping on thy Hat, or diſprove our taking it off to perſons, as a Vain <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian Practice?</hi> and as to many other things I might men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Moreover as concerning Womens Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, ſomething further.</p>
               <p>As the Chriſtian Women in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Goſpel-times had their Services in the Church, as the Spirit of Truth then led and guided them, which was and is unlimited (and what does thou know <hi>Fr.</hi> but the Lord Jeſus did then encourage
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64952:22"/>them in the ſame?) So the Chriſtian Women in this our Goſpel day, having received a meaſure of the ſame Spirit, and as they walk in the Leadings and Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings thereof (which I believe certainly many do) know and ſee their Services ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed them of God, and by him are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to perform their Duty.</p>
               <p>Obſerve, The Apoſtle ſpeaks of the <hi>Elder Women</hi> as <hi>Mothers,</hi> and <hi>the Aged were to Teach the Young Women to be ſober,</hi> &amp;c. Tit. 2.3, 4.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Joſephus</hi> (in his Antiquites, <hi>p.</hi> 706.) ſpeaks of a peculiar place deſtinated for <hi>Women</hi> for Religion ſake, where as they exerciſed their <hi>Devotion,</hi> ſo no doubt but they performed their <hi>Services for the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification one of another,</hi> and <hi>doing good to ſuch as they were related to and concerned with.</hi> And p. 60. he ſaith, <hi>The Women alſo ſtrove with Emulation to exceed each other in the Work and Service; to the Honour of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Third Volumn of the <hi>Book of Martyrs,</hi> p. 24. Ann. 1563. And in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign. Its ſaid as followeth.</p>
               <q>An outrage done to poor Women, who met together to comfort one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </q>
               <q>There was an <hi>Honeſt Woman</hi> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity of <hi>Bois,</hi> whoſe Name was <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chale,</hi> the wiſe of one <hi>John Lemanche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:64952:22"/>Maker of Sun-Dials, in whoſe Houſe certain Neighbours meeting together, to Comfort and Edifie one another, and to pray one with and for another, to the number of Nine, or there-a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts, with their Daughters; theſe Murderers hearing of it, ran violently in among them, thinking to have found a Miniſter Preaching to them; but when. they ſaw how they were miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, they dragged them out by the Hair of the Head into the midſt of the Street, where leading them with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of Stripes, they caſt them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the River; in which Calamity God endued them with ſuch ſtrength and skill, being unbound, that endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſwim, at length they arrived at an <hi>Iſle,</hi> they being ſeized upon by ſome Ferry Men, they were ſtript naked, and then thrown again into the River, and thinking yet to ſave themſelves, they were in the end knocked down by the ſeditious in the Suburbs of <hi>Vienna.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>Now by this Spirit of Truth the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Women are directed and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to diſcharge the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r Duty aforeſaid, in their taking care of the Poor &amp; Fatherleſs, &amp; other good Chriſtian profitable Services, as the ſame directs them; and the Lord both attends them by his Counſel and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:64952:23"/>Wiſdom, and alſo countenances them with his Living, Divine, Refreſhing Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in their Meetings, and by him are the Faithful Women juſtified, whoever may condemn them.</p>
               <p>And we do very well know that as his living eternal power hath ſet up and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed our publick ſolemn Aſſemblies, and our <hi>Mens Meetings,</hi> ſo I do confidently affirm from ſenbleſi well grounded experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; as I have been many times an eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſs, the ſame hath eſtabliſhed <hi>Womens Meetings;</hi> and I am fully ſatisfied with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt heſitation or ſcruple in my mind, that now which hath and doth give authority to the former, to render them lawful, attends the latter, to authoriſe and render them both lawful and laudable.</p>
               <p>Therefore I may ſafely ſay, that Spirit which oppoſes, abuſes and deſpiſes the <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> in their reſpective Chriſtian ſervices, and would not allow them the liberty which they have in Chriſt their Head and Husband, is the <hi>Dark wicked Spirit of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,</hi> &amp;c. which condemns that which God juſtifies and approves of, and ſo an abomination before him: and I am truly ſenſible, that thoſe joyned thereunto, I mean thee <hi>F.</hi> and ſuch like to thee, who through that rancour and radicated Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:64952:23"/>have hardned your ſelves (I am afraid) to deſtruction, and not all who through ignorance or ſimplicity are betrayed by your crafty deſigns and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle inſinuations to favour your work, ſuch as ſtand in oppoſition to, and ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the <hi>Womens Meetings,</hi> that though they ſeem firſt and moſtly to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy againſt Womens Meetings (and as I remember follows or imitates the old Serpent, who firſt ſet upon the <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> by his Temptations with a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to gain ground upon the <hi>Man</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards) yet the ſame wicked ranting looſe libertine Spirit, that cries out ſo vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently away with our <hi>Womens Meetings</hi> (as thou in thy ſcoffing Airy Mind abuſes them, comparing them to the <hi>Papiſts great Idol,</hi> viz. the <hi>Roob of Grace,</hi> to <hi>Graceleſs <hi>as well as</hi> Lifeleſs Image</hi> (ſee <hi>p.</hi> 8. and 47.) will not only deſcry <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Preaching</hi> as ſome of them have done already) but alſo at laſt would over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn our <hi>Mens Meetings,</hi> and ſo would bring all things topſiturvey,<note place="margin">Theſe are indeed the <hi>Babel</hi> Builders.</note> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide down, into a meer <hi>Chaos,</hi> Diſorder and Confuſion again, and here would be (which the Devil would be at, and mainly ſeeks) an open door for <hi>Libertiniſm,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64952:24"/>Ranteriſm, Atheiſm, Profanity,</hi> and all maner of <hi>Debauchery.</hi> But God Almighty will overthrow all theſe deviliſh Deſigns and helliſh Imaginations, and Truth and Righteouſneſs hath he decreed to eſtabliſh in the Earth, ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly magnified be his holy Name for ever, for he is worthy over all to be feared, ſerved and obeyed by all the Sons and Daughters of Men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>NOw I come to the firſt Chapter of <hi>F. Bugg</hi>'s Book, p. 24. in the which he pretends to treat of <hi>Principles of Truth received and believed in the beginning,</hi> &amp;c. wherein there is but little of weight to be noticed, being but a ſlender imperfect Relation thereof, and that too, with a crafty, ſubttle Deſign to ſtrike againſt Friends of Truth, maliciouſly thereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuating to the World, <hi>How it was ſo and ſo with them in the beginning, and now other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This living Teſtimony I have to bear to the contrary, that (bleſſed be the name of the Lord) the ſame foundation principle and corner ſtone that was laid in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:64952:24"/>for the building of Gods Spiritual Houſe, is as precious to us now as ever; and is of as great eſteem, and we do preach the ſame, and no other; even the ſaving ſufficient Divine <hi>Light of Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> and the Spiritual appearance thereof; and it is our work and labour to direct and turn the minds of people to be inward and retired thereunto, as unto the more ſure word of Prophecy; and that there is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency in it, being obeyed, to lead to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: and as we are come to the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the holy Unction, and feel and taſte of the ſweetneſs, excellency and vertue thereof in our own particulars, ſo we declare thereof unto others, that they might be ſtirred up to wait upon the Lord with us in his heavenly Gift, and have the ſame ſenſe and experience in themſelves, and ſo ſee and taſte for themſelves: and bleſſed be God, our love one to another. doth abound, and our zeal for his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oly name doth encreaſe, and a heavenly harmony of life ſounds in our Aſſemblies as in the beginning, in which ſtands our Unity &amp; Fellowſhip, and there are many who are living witneſſes by how much the more we are ſpiritually minded and ſeriouſly exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in the inward Teſtimony or Law of the Spirit of Life, and the more we take delight to meditate therein Night and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:64952:25"/>Day, by ſo much the more the Lord is pleaſed to maifeſt his Love unto us, and to reveal his pure Power amongſt us, and is our Hedge and Wall to this Day, and gives us favour in the ſight of the People, glorified be his pure name for ever.</p>
               <p>And we do teſtifie in a holy freſh zeal againſt all ſuch <hi>Formalities, Will worſhips, Church-Authorities, Ceremonies, Orders, Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions,</hi> as are neither uſeful, decent nor comely in the ſight of God; and our Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony lives &amp; remains as in the beginning (everlaſting praiſe to the Almighty) againſt all that Traſh and Trumpery of the <hi>Whore</hi> of <hi>Babylon,</hi> brought in and ſet up in the dark Night of Apoſtacy; and we do teſtifie, That Chriſt &amp; his Kingdom is to be known within, not in any Obſervation or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion that is Viſible, without the poſſeſſion and inward enjoyment of him; and he, even the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> the Lord from Heaven, is head of, and Lawgiver to our Church, on whoſe ſhoulders the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Authority thereof is laid. And we know, that though in the World there are Faiths many, and Lords many; yet unto us there is but one Faith, and one Lord Jeſus Chriſt: who is the Author of that Faith.</p>
               <p>And we have an honourable eſteem of the Scriptures of Truth, and they are very
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:64952:25"/>good, and uſeful in their place, and they are by us believed, and a great comfort and bleſſing to us; but ſtill the ſpirit of God is the firſt Principle, the Pale, and only Head of the true Church, and Sanctified people of God; and is likewiſe the Rule of our Life and Practice, and always hath the preheminence in our Teſtimony, as ever from the beginning: this we have declared, and do declare on all occaſions, to all People, Profeſſor, and Prophane, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſuch as are faithful to the Lord, will not queſtion the truth of this, as it is at preſent witneſſed (Everlaſting praiſes to the Lord over all.) And theſe need not go for proof thereof, as thou ſaiſt pag. 28. <hi>to ſuch and ſuch Teſtimonies of thoſe good faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Servants of the Lord, who did bear a Noble Teſtimony againſt all Apoſtates and Back-ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> as the Reader may ſee in a Book of our worthy Friend <hi>Iſaac Penington</hi> (whom <hi>F.B.</hi> mentions) concerning <hi>Church Government.</hi> For we have a certain evidence and many clear tokens of the powerful, divine, and refreſhing preſence of the Almighty God attending us in our holy Services and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Practiſes, both in our <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Womens Meetings,</hi> which ſhall ſtand and in Glory remain, when thou and all ſuch claſhing jarring, jangling, and perverſe prating ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits ſhall vaniſh and be no more ſeen in this
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:64952:26"/>World. And indeed, I know for certain, and many times it hath livingly and with unſpeakable comfort opened in mé, when I have had occaſion to be under any ſad Exerciſe, by any of this Oppoſite Party, <hi>that their wild and haſty furious Contentions and malicious Endeavours, againſt the Goſpel Order in the Church of Chriſt, is but another <hi>ſmoak</hi>
                  </hi> (though one of the blackeſt and thickeſt) <hi>that is come up, or may be, may hereaftercome up from the <hi>Bottomleſs Pit.</hi> And the breath of the Lord God Almighty is ſcattering of it, and will blow it quite away, ſo that it (as we have ſeen other <hi>ſmoaks</hi>) ſhall utterly diſappear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the wiſe prudent <hi>Reader</hi> may obſerve, that many of the Epiſtles of Advice and Counſels to Friends from their Meetings, nothing now more than in the beginning implies any impoſition or force thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; and they are ſo worded as that <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty</hi> is preſerved, and the <hi>people not impoſed upon beyond their freedom;</hi> and that it is ſo I ſhall prove in the next Chapter.</p>
               <p>And ſo we plainly ſee that the Devil and his Agents have but befooled themſelves by falſely inſinuating to any, as this <hi>F.B.</hi> doth in page 31. <hi>That we exerciſe Dominion, Gentile-like, and with Lording over Gods Heritage:</hi> for the ſame <hi>Chriſtian Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:64952:26"/>diſcenſion</hi> and <hi>true moderation</hi> appears amongſt us as in the beginning.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>IN page 32. <hi>F. B.</hi> ſays, <hi>I am now to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt the alteration and the cauſe of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions amongſt us about Matters of Faith, and the exerciſe of it, Church Diſcipline, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Poor Man! Thou look'ſt far abroad to ſeek the Cauſe of Diviſion, and little minds to look at home in thine own Houſe; and for all thy vain inſolent Braggs and proud Boaſtings, in bringing thy proof, That there is <hi>Violence, Tyranny,</hi> and what not, done to our firſt Principles of Union; cite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>W. P</hi>'s Saying in his Addreſs to Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> pag. 149. <q>That Perſwaſion and Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on began all true Chriſtian Societies; and whether his violence upon this part, Tyranny and not Order is introduced, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> — I ſay it is a Lie in thee to inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the contrary as to us; and <hi>Reader,</hi> to evince the ſame, conſider but the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Proof, for which he inſerts <hi>G. F</hi>'s <hi>New Order</hi> (as he in his flouring mind terms it) wrote about the year 71. for <hi>Womens Meetings</hi> to be held <hi>Diſtinct from
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:64952:27"/>Mens Meetings, and was confirm'd after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> (as he ſays) <hi>by a General Council or Yearly Meeting,</hi> &amp;c. viz <hi>Dear Friends, To whom is my love in that which chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges not, it would do well, and be of ſervice for you, to have a Womens Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as they have in other parts,</hi> &amp;c. I refer thee to the peruſal of the reſt of <hi>G.F.</hi>'s Epiſtle, which I believe he wrote from a ſenſe of the holy Power, and ſee if thou canſt find any thing therein like unto im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, violence, or alteration, done to our firſt Principles of Union.</p>
               <p>In page 38. he ſcoffingly and imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently ſays, <hi>At the Yearly Meeting or Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Council held at</hi> London, <hi>in the year</hi> 75. <hi>The ſaid Grant or Order was ſtrengthneed and confirmed in all points, and with as much Policy as ever the Learned Biſhops or Grave Senates, uſed to eſtabliſh their Monarchical Governments,</hi> &amp;c. The underſtanding <hi>Reader</hi> may perceive his weakneſs and folly here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
               <p>And in page 40. he greatly braggs, to <hi>give both proof and preſident, of what he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuated,</hi> and ſo tranſcribes ſomething, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>propounding of Marriages,</hi> which he calls, <hi>the confirmation of the Foundation of the Womens Meetings</hi> (<hi>namely,</hi> G. F. <hi>his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der above recited</hi> (<hi>by a General Council held at</hi> London, <hi>Anno</hi> 1675.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:64952:27"/>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>
                        <hi>London,</hi> 27. 3 Mo. 75.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IT is our Judgment, That for better ſatisfaction to all parties, that there may be due time for Enquiry of Clearneſs of the perſons concerned, it is conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that Marriages be twice propounded to the Meetings that are to take care therein, both to the</hi> Mens <hi>and</hi> Womens Meetings, <hi>where both are eſtabliſhed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are accompliſhed; and when things are cleared, that the Marriage be accompliſhed in a Grave and Publick Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of Friends or Relations.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>I have ſet this down <hi>verbatim</hi> as I found it in <hi>F. B</hi>'s Book, wherein thou maiſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, Firſt, It's ſaid, <hi>It is our Judgment, that for better ſatisfaction to all parties,</hi> &amp;c. (not for <hi>Impoſition</hi> upon any.) Secondly, <hi>It is convenient</hi> (here's a <hi>good cauſe</hi> and <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi>) And Thirdly, <hi>Where both are eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed,</hi> &amp;c. For my part he muſt ſee fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than I can, that draws ſuch an Unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Concluſion from the premiſes of <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, Violence,</hi> or <hi>Tyranny,</hi> done to the firſt Principles of our Union.</p>
               <p>But to prove yet the ſame, it ſeems he is ſomewhat pinched, for he ſtrains and ſnatches greedily every thing he can to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:64952:28"/>make out his matter. In pag. 42. he ſaith, <hi>I am neceſſitated to tranſcribe more of the tranſactions of this Notable, if not <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Council, than I am willing</hi> (Alas! that ever thou ſhould'ſt have been ſo willing to ſerve the Devil at ſuch a rate as thou does; too too willing <hi>Francis</hi> to make uſe of all thy ſtrength to hatch out of Hell and plod in the dark, if thou canſt thereby but abuſe an innocent people) <hi>leſt</hi> G. W. <hi>ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain call for a Proof or Catalogue of their new <hi>ſtamped Government:</hi>
                  </hi> And to this end he inſerts another paper which Friends wrote concerning <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Womens Meetings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is our Judgment and Teſtimony in the Word of Gods Wiſdom, that the riſe and practice, ſetting up, and eſtabliſhment of Mens and Womens Meetings in the Church of Chriſt in this our day and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, is according to the mind and counſel of God, and done in the endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his eternal Spirit; and that it is the duty of all Friends and Brethren in the power of God in all places to be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent therein, and to encourage and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther each other in that bleſſed work,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I refer the Reader to conſider the reſt of this, and compare it and the former with a Letter of advice and counſel for the help and information of the weak and lately convinced, pag. 28. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:64952:28"/>in he ſays, <hi>It was ſo worded, as that</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Liberty <hi>was preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and the People not impoſed upon beyond their freedom.</hi> And ſee if there be ſuch a vaſt difference as he would inſinuate in pag. 45. <hi>Behold</hi> (ſays he) <hi>the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this Decree and the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">n="*" Yet in that I do not find Chap. nor verſe of <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke,</hi> or <hi>John;</hi> which he calls for ſo much.</note> 
                  <hi>Letter of Advice and Counſel inn the firſt Chapter,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>That was not propoſed otherwiſe then Adviſe and Counſel, and not as a Form or Rule to walk by, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>ANd <hi>Reader,</hi> That thou maiſt ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Author either looks like to be a ſober diſcreet prudent Man, or like a <hi>true Chriſtian Quaker,</hi> as he and <hi>W. R.</hi> and ſome few of their party would be reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves, <hi>as only ſuch;</hi> I will here inſert ſomething of his flouting Mockery and idle Drollery in his Obſervations up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the fore-going paper, and indeed the greateſt part of his Book (I mean this Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part, and what properly may be termed his) is ſtuffed up with ſuch imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent Stories and uncivil Reflections.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:64952:29"/>
               <p>In pag. 46. <hi>But</hi> (ſays he) <hi>to make good proviſion againſt any that ſhall yet dare to ſlight this new Model or new found Method of Church Government, or call in queſtion their power and authority, ſee what a ſtrict and ſevere Admonition is uttered forth, even as if it had come from the</hi> Popes Council <hi>of</hi> Jeſuits and <hi>Crafty</hi> Friars, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In pag. 47. and ſpeaking of Womens Meetings, <hi>I ſay, if it be ſo, why ſhould not the</hi> Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copalians, Presbiterians, Independants, Baptiſts, <hi>&amp;c. know of them</hi> (and why not? as many of them do, of which we are not aſhamed, if all the World knew it; and by the ſober part of them are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended therefore) <hi>but if it be a meer Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination of their own brain</hi> (I think ſtrange, <hi>Francis,</hi> thou haſt now ſo much diſcretion as but to ſuppoſe it, and ſay <hi>[If]</hi> to it, it ſeems it ſticks a little in thy throat, and thou wouldſt fain come out with a poſitive Aſſertion, if it were not an abſolute down-right Lie, of which it may be thou art con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious thy ſelf to the contrary, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore couldſt not determine that it is meer Imagination, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) <hi>and an Idol of their own erecting, why ſhould it not publickly be brought to Light, and made as manifeſt as the Lord</hi> Crumwel <hi>made the</hi> Papiſts great Idol, <hi>viz. the <hi>Rood of Grace</hi>
                  </hi> (<hi>which had gogling eyes,</hi> thou ſain, <hi>and would ſmile when a good gift
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:64952:29"/>was offered to it) when he cauſed it to be brought to</hi> Pauls Croſs, <hi>where the People tore it all to peices in King</hi> Henry <hi>the Eighths time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Francis,</hi> Pray tell me, Couldſt thou find it in thy heart to uſe the Women and their Meetings ſo? A body would think that ſuch a groſs wicked thing were far off from thy very thoughts, much leſs to do ſo wickedly, if it were in thy power.</p>
               <p>But alas! what thou haſt publickly print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and falſly inſinuated to the World, that we are <hi>Impoſers, Apoſtates,</hi> and <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vators,</hi> and like to the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and are introducing <hi>Blind Obedience</hi> and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit Faith,</hi> and <hi>that G. F. and his part are more ſevere than the Biſhops of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Churches;</hi> ſee pag. 195. Theſe and many more malicious ſuggeſtions do they not be ſpeak thy fury and envy, and may not many ſuſpect that thou wouldſt gladly that both our Men and Women Friends, and their Meetings too, were expoſed to the Rage, Violence, and Cruelty of our Enemies and Perſecutors, thereby to tear us in pieces.</p>
               <p>Tell me, <hi>Francis,</hi> Would it not ſadly grieve thee to ſee us ſo uſed, as Lord <hi>Thomas Cromwel</hi> in <hi>K. H's</hi> time cauſe the <hi>Papiſts Rood of Grace</hi> to be torn in pieces? Would not thine heart be ſore to ſee ſuch a diſmal Tragedy? Some
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:64952:30"/>may be rather think thou wouldſt rathe rejoyce at it, and may be as buſie as any of them to add fewel to the fire, and help forwards their work of Perſecution, as <hi>W. R.</hi> and <hi>T. C.</hi> have done, and are doing what in you lies, becauſe they may ſafely judge, whout breach of Charity, that Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Envy, Slander and Malice, by which you are guided naturally, leads to it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame ground in you from whence all Perſecution hath proceeded.</p>
               <p>And therefore if ſuch work as this pleaſe thee (I do not poſitively affirm it doth) would not this ſhew the very worſt part of the <hi>Spirit of Popery;</hi> and too like the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Inquiſition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I pray God to pity thee and the reſt of thy Abettors, and if it may ſtand with his holy will to forgive you, and open your eyes to ſee the evil of your ways, and what you have cruelly acted againſt him and his faithful innocent People, This is the worſt I wiſh you, I can upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay, and God knoweth <hi>I</hi> lie not.</p>
               <p>But to proceed, <hi>I</hi> will give thee, <hi>Reader,</hi> a further reliſh of this ſcoffing Spirit that hath prevailed upon this Author <hi>F. B.</hi> (if ſo be he is the very Pen-man or Compi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of all this Second Part, for I have my own reaſon to ſuſpect ſome other Perſon to be concerned therein; <hi>I</hi> mean as to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:64952:30"/>the bulk of it; for I find <hi>J. A</hi>'s. name in pag. 87. whether <hi>F. B.</hi> had power from <hi>J. A.</hi> to inſert this, yea or nay, <hi>I</hi> cannot tell:) making his Obſervations upon the riſe, practice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the Womens Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings according to the mind and counſel of God and the ordering of his Eternal Spirit, which bleſſed be his holy Name, many are living Witneſſes this day, who can ſet their ſeal to the verity thereof, from their ſenſible experience of his ſweet refreſhing preſence, countenancing us in our Men and Womens Meetings. — <hi>Whereby</hi> (ſays <hi>F. B.</hi> in his ordinary ſtrain of mockery) <hi>G. F. his erection of this as New as Needleſs Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, is ratified by theſe preſents, according</hi> to their <hi>true intent and meaning; No <hi>Pope</hi> ever had a more true and loyal Council, or one better skilled, or more politick,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Is not <hi>F. B</hi> a plain Mocker and foolish Scoffer.</note> 
                  <hi>to ſave his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs from any danger, or confirm his infallible and unerring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nstitutions; nay further, I think they have granted to him his heirs and ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors for ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r, I ſee no limit in the whole Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cal Cannon.</hi> And (in pag. 56.) he ſays thus — <hi>So that upon the whole matter, I cannot ſee what could have hindred the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleating this Grant and Confiirmation, had they put theſe four branches to the remaining ſix</hi> (for they are in all twelve particulars)
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:64952:31"/>
                  <hi>and obtained their paſſing both Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and the Royall aſſent; the neglect whereof hath been greatly d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſadvantageous to their carrying on their then notable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reader,</hi> What maiſt thou conclude, hath this Man the ſtile of a <hi>true like Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Quaker,</hi> or <hi>ſober diſcreet Man?</hi> No ſurely, one may more ſafely judge (without any breach of Charity) he is more like to a <hi>rambling Droller</hi> or <hi>Stage-player,</hi> and an abſolute <hi>Prophane Mocker,</hi> in his baſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſavoury expreſſions; and a great deal of ſuch I could mention, had I either leaſure or delight to trace him throughly. — But as we uſe to ſay, <hi>A Dogs bark is no ſlander.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In pag 58, 59. He moſt maliciouſly ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſts, to amuſe people (ignorant of us) with ſtrange apprehenſions and harſh thoughts concerning us. <hi>We</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that differ from others, and deſires their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance, yet at the ſame time, differing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our ſelves, cannot, nay, will not bear one with another.</hi> (A humble lie) <hi>We cry to the Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſtrates for the liberty and free ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of our Conſciences in Matters Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and will not, nay, reſolves not, come what will come, to allow the free exerciſe of Conſcience in Matters Spiritual to our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Brethren. Oh depth of hypocriſie and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:64952:31"/>fore-runner of Tyranny! ſhould you have power put into your hands, be ſo you Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> eyes are a little opened to ſee your Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, your Double Dealing, your Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Dealing,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Is not this Man a Compleat Syſtem both of groſs Lies and Envy, and alſo of Malice, Rancor and Drollery?</p>
               <p>And in pag. 71. <hi>But too much like the</hi> Papiſts, <hi>implicitely believe as the Church believes, practiſe as the Church practiſes, and in all points yield obedience to her Decrees without any examination, ſcruple, or doubt; or elſe why ſhould that abettor of the cauſe of</hi> G. F. <hi>adviſe as followeth? viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Let not this Spirit be reaſoned with, enter not into Propoſals and Articles with it, but feed it with Judgment, that is Gods Decree.</q>
               <p>By thy Obſervations on this, it ſeems thou doeſt not underſtand what that means, ſaying, <hi>Mark the tendancy of this advice; for ſhould the Apoſtles have thus preached to the</hi> Bereans, <hi>what liberty had been left for their ſearch and further exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination? Nay, Chriſt himſelf reaſoned in the Synagogue of the Jews, and the Apoſtles did the like, a free Debate was admited when any difference aroſe amongſt them, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us is ſtiffly denied.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is; <hi>Reader, firſt</hi> a wicked Slander
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:64952:32"/>and Oli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>um caſt upon us, ſuggeſting falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y <hi>we are too much like to Papiſts,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His ignorance of that ſentence <hi>of one of</hi> G. F's <hi>abettor,</hi> as he calls him; Its that <hi>treacherous, deceitful, perfidious, oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite <hi>Spirit,</hi> and not the <hi>Perſons</hi>
                  </hi> joyned thereto, we are not to reaſon with, and which is to be fed with Judgment, and will be, I know certainly its Gods Decree; and its well known what pains and labour we have taken to reclaim and recover ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who have been betrayed by their reaſonings and conſultings with that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful curſed Spirit of Separation, and the Lord has bleſſed our endeavours there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and our earneſt Cry to him, <hi>That none may be loſt but the Son of Perdition:</hi> ſuch who are ſimply and ignorantly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed, I hope may be reſtored into Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with God and his People (as many are) who have true honeſty, or rather an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt right ground, remaining in them. <hi>But for thoſe who have ſinned wilfully</hi> (as the Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> writes) <hi>after they have received the knowledg of the truth, there remaineth no more ſacrifice for ſins, but a fearful looking for of judgment and fiery indignation, which ſhall devour the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries:</hi> and ſo goes on, and gives the reaſons, and concludes with a ſevere ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, <hi>It's a fearful thing to fall into the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:64952:32"/>hands of the Living God, who is a conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fire:</hi> Heb. 10.26, 27. For ſuch who ſpeaks lies in hypocriſie, having their Conſciences ſeared with a hot Iron, whoſe hearts are quite hardned, and become twice dead, plucked up by the roots; whoſe day of viſitation is expired by their reiterated abominable provocations and rebellion, I fear ſuch are hardned to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and judicially ſealed up to damnation.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Thirdly,</hi> There is a notorious Lie. For when any difference ariſes amongſt us, there is a free Conference and ſober Debating thereof admited, to reconcile and reſolve the ſame; ſo that he lies, in ſaying, That <hi>both by our practice and advice it's ſtiffly denied.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In pag. 101. <hi>Come give us Chapter and verſe for your Womens Meeting diſtinct from the Men, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly ſet up (unleſs a litle</hi>
                  <note place="margin">n="*" When that comes, we have ſeen by many obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable Inſtances, how theſe <hi>Separates</hi> have crept into holes of the Earth to ſave themſelves from <hi>Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> much like to the Flies, when it's warm Weather, they vex both Men and Beaſts, but hardly to be ſeen, when Winter comes.</note> 
                  <hi>cold weather intervene) Monthly about the 10th hour, to get a litle ſtock; we ſuppoſe thou meaneſt</hi> (ſpeaking to <hi>G. F.</hi>) <hi>a lttle money for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſelect uſes; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a more private way than the Baſon and Platter,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:64952:33"/>
               <p>We ſay to thee <hi>F. Bugg</hi> and all Profeſſors by way of retortion, <hi>Come give us expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Chapter and verſe for Mens meeting toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to take care of the poor Widows and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs, at ſuch a place in ſuch a Month, and of ſuch an hour of the day;</hi> as thou putteſt us upon proof concerning Womens. Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, in pag. 101. Couldſt thou bring Chap. and verſe in expreſs terms for the proof of the former (which thou alloweſt of to be <hi>Lawful</hi>) as with reſpect to <hi>place, Month,</hi> and <hi>hour</hi> of the <hi>Day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Query. <hi>And ought not then the Men to meet together, to diſcharge the foreſaid Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Duties, unleſs thou canſt bring expreſly Chap. and verſe to prove their practice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as with reſpect to place, month, and hour? If thou ſay, Nay, Then has not this a tendency to overthrow Mens Meetings, as well as the Womens Meetings?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though we know in the holy Scriptures of truth, there is plentiful encouragment for both <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Women</hi> to ſerve God, and each other in love and faithfulneſs; and though divers Circumſtances relative to <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Womens Meetings,</hi> as <hi>day, hour, month, and place,</hi> cannot be proved from expreſs words of Scripture, yet the <hi>Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Women,</hi> and their appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (in the wiſdom of God) <hi>day, hour, month,</hi> and <hi>place,</hi> is not contrary to the Scriptures.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:64952:33"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>For now any rational perſon may conceive that it were groſly abſurd and irrational, to affirm that every good act or thing done, which cannot be proved by expreſs plain Scripture words, without any ſound inference and true conſequence, is therefore contrary to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſider this ſeriouſly and in the cool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and calmneſs of thy mind, and I hope thou willt not be ſo ſtout in <hi>oppoſing Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens</hi> Meetings as thou haſt been, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I deſire thee and the reſt of thy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in miſchief, to conſider what the wiſe man expreſſes in Eccleſiaſticus, <hi>A Back-biting Tongue hath caſt out <hi>vertuous women,</hi> and deprived them of their labours; who ſo hearkneth unto it ſhall never find reſt, and never dwell quietly:</hi> Eccl. 28.15, 16.</p>
               <p>And to compleat thy Draught of Moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kery, maliciouſly and unſeemly abuſing that worthy ancient Labourer of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel <hi>G. F.</hi> by thy propoſing a <hi>Battledore,</hi> and in thy flouting airy mind ſets within it the form of <hi>Spectacles,</hi> in pag. 163. thereby to beget a light wanton mind in the People; and ſo makes but thy ſelf a Mocking ſtock, or the fooliſh like to thy ſelf, to deride thee, and the ſober to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſte and diſdain thy ſcurrilous, baſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy doings.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:64952:34"/>
               <p>May not I now ſay unto thee for theſe and many more of thy unchriſtian defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, malicious ſuggeſtions, and inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane reflections, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas?</hi> Art not like to him in his wicked work? Haſt not thou by this Deviliſh piece of treachery, withſtood the Lord and his Servants, and thereby <hi>endeavoured to turn away many from the faith of Gods elect. Thou enemy of all righteouſneſs, thou Child of the Devil; O full of all ſubtilty! wilt thou not ceaſe to pervert the right wayes of the Lord?</hi> And now behold the hand of the Lord is againſt thee, and if thou humble not thy ſelf ſpeedily under the ſame, moſt lamentable ſhall thy ſtate be, when thou muſt bid an everlaſting Adieu to all thy comforts, pleaſures, and riches, thou en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyeſt in this life: <hi>God grant thou mayeſt find a place for repentance.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>IN pag. 63. <hi>F. B.</hi> inſerts an Order record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the <hi>Quarterly Meeting Book</hi> in the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Ely,</hi> which I leave to thoſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly concerned to take notice of; but ſuppoſing that they had done amiſs, which I do not grant, pray tell me what
<pb facs="tcp:64952:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>reaſon or juſtice is it, as amongſt men, that a whole Nation or Body of People, ſhould be charged ſo and ſo with the fault of a particular County, or any one Quarterly Meeting.</p>
               <p>Moſt part of this Chapter relates to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſons to anſwer, if they find it worthy the pains.</p>
               <p>But he makes ſuch a buſtle and noiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>J. A</hi>'s Marriage, its meet ſomething ſhould be particularly hinted at as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſame.</p>
               <p>Our Friends for Conſcience ſake could not own nor countenance <hi>J. A</hi>'s Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, which he would impoſe on us to own, without the Womans appearing, whom he intended to take. And is this <hi>W. R</hi>'s and <hi>F.B</hi>'s Conſcience, that we muſt own <hi>J.A</hi>'s Marraige to a Woman that comes not with him to the Mens Meeting to declare her mind (for we know our Womens Meetings they are againſt and diſregard. And we muſt declare its a matter of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to us in the Caſe of <hi>J. A.</hi> or any other, <hi>for him to come to our Meeting and tell us, that he intends to take his Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper to be his Wife;</hi> and we deſire him to bring her to our Mens Meeting to hear what ſhe ſays to it: And he ſays, <hi>He is not free to bring her to declare that ſhe intends to take him to be her Husband</hi>) that we may
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:64952:35"/>hear both parties: And if he make a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Conſcience of this to let the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hear what ſhe ſaith, but we muſt take his word without hearing the Woman what ſhe ſays; and if he be aſhamed of her to appear before the Meetings toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is not this <hi>wilfulneſs?</hi> We have no Unity with ſuch. If a Man ſhould come to one of our Meetings, and ſay, <hi>I would take ſuch a mans daughter to Wife;</hi> you will impoſe upon us, that we muſt have Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with it; and he will not bring the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with him, nor Relations, that we may have ſatisfaction from their mouths (or by a Certificate) and hear what they ſay to it; ſuch Marriages we can have no Unity with. And if <hi>W. R. F. B.</hi> and <hi>T. C.</hi> that was married with a Prieſt, can nurſe up ſuch, we ſay, we have no Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip nor Unity with them as be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, civil, modeſt, and of good report; for we would have the ſatisfaction of the <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Woman,</hi> and their <hi>Relations</hi> alſo, that all things may be done decent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and in good Order; that no Man or Woman, or Relations, may be wronged: for <hi>our God is a God of Order, and not of Confuſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now <hi>Reader,</hi> thou may'ſt eaſily diſcern whether we or they be the <hi>Impoſers</hi> and <hi>Innovators. F. B.</hi> and <hi>W. R</hi>'s new Order,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:64952:35"/>Traditions, Preſcriptions, Impoſitions, and Innovations, is, that <hi>J. A.</hi> or another Man, muſt tell his intention of Marriage without the Woman being there, to know her mind; and this is their new Way, new Order, and new Method: And this was <hi>J. H</hi>'s way (at the <hi>Peel</hi>) and the Woman <hi>M. P.</hi> was not there, who when ſhe heard of it, ſhe utterly denied him: And ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in <hi>Kent</hi> did ſo fooliſhly declare he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to take a Woman not preſent there, which grieved her ſore, when ſhe heard of it.</p>
               <p>And ſo by this new Order, Preſcription, and Innovation, which <hi>F. B.</hi> and <hi>W. R.</hi> would impoſe on us to have Unity with, <hi>Women</hi> may be greatly <hi>wronged</hi> and their <hi>Relations abuſed</hi> by every bad looſe Man, and make people believe that their conſent is to it, when it is not; and ſo be ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalized and offended: therefore to prevent which, we do judg that in the Wiſdom of God the <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Woman</hi> ought both to come together, when they lay their intentions of Marriage before a Meeting, and their Relations to be ſatisfied; and if they live far off beyond Sea or in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther County, then to have a Certificate from them that they are ſatisfied: And this I underſtand hath been our Friends practice before thee <hi>F. B.</hi> came amongſt
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:64952:36"/>us, and will remain, I doubt not, when thou art gone.</p>
               <p>Other particulars I would mention, whereby it may be juſtly repelled upon <hi>W. R. F. B.</hi> &amp;c. that they are the <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vators</hi> and <hi>Impoſers,</hi> but what I have ſet down already may ſerve as a ſufficient proof at preſent.</p>
               <p>In pag. 74. there are ſome Queries, ſtrange ſort of ones as I have read; <hi>viz. Whether Chriſt Jeſus, the true God and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, in whom the fulneſs of the God-head dwelt bod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly, be the Head of the true Church? Or whether</hi> George Fox, <hi>who is but a Man, unto whom the Spirit is given but by mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, be head thereof?</hi> His ſecond Query is an Anſwer to the firſt, and the third to the ſecond, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I wonder much <hi>F. B.</hi> has ſhewn ſo much diſcretion and civility, as to confeſs (but I believe he cannot otherways do) that we acknowledg Chriſt Jeſus to be both the Head, Ruler, and Lawgiver of the true Church.</p>
               <p>But then in his Fifth Query he ſeems to boaſt greatly, and brag at a high rate, as if (forſooth poor Man) he had gained all (how wiſe is a fool in his own vain conceit, what his empty noddle or brain doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, that he judges none can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove?) <hi>If you ſay that Chriſt nor his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:64952:36"/>left neither command, example, nor pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident for Womens Meetings,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>then I que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry further of you the ſaid Impoſers, where had you your power, or from whence had you your Authority to inſtitute ſuch a way of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in the Church, by Women or other ways, containing ſuch Rites and Ceremonies; and in whoſe name do you compel to an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity and Conformity thereto?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What I have formerly ſaid in Chap. 4 may be enough to anſwer the foreſaid Query; but in ſhort, I ſay again, from the Lord God of Heaven and Earth his People have received power, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with are they endued to perform thoſe <hi>Holy Chriſtian Practices</hi> in their <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Womens Meetings;</hi> and thereby are they inveſted with Authority and Dominion to ſtand up as Noble Witneſſes for the <hi>Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard of Righteouſneſs</hi> againſt <hi>all oppoſition:</hi> and by how much the more we are ſaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and ſingly reſigned in a holy Zeal and due diligence to attend and wait upon the Lord in our Meetings to perform that which tends to his Glory, and the good of one another, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by ſo much the more doth he countenance us with his divine comfortable preſence; and therefore we are not careful, nor need we be troubled what unruly, diſorderly, looſe, ranting Spirits, ſuch as are given to a <hi>Fleſhly li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:64952:37"/>and <hi>wanton mind,</hi> ſay to the contrary, queſtion, or condemn us therefore.</p>
               <p>And I may ſay as an encouragement to you that are faithful to the Lord in your ſervices, both in your <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Womens Meetings,</hi> as the holy Apoſtle ſaid in his day to the <hi>Philippians; Whatſoever things are true, whatſoever things are honeſt, whatſoever things are juſt, whatſoever things are pure, whatſoever things are lovely, whatſoever things are of good report, if there be any vertue, and if there be any praiſe, think on theſe things;</hi> and not onely ſo, but <hi>thoſe things,</hi> ſays he, <hi>which ye have both learned and received, and heard and ſeen in me, do, and the God of peace ſhall be with you;</hi> Phil. 4.8, 9.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Francis,</hi> that's an abſolute plain for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery to imply by way of Query (taking it for granted that it were really ſo) in whoſe Name do we compel to a Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For we do deny it as feigned and falſe, and many living powerful Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies ariſe in the hearts of Gods Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren againſt this wicked, malicious, abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Spirit, that would defame us by falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuggeſting we did compel, force and drive People <hi>(nolens volens)</hi> againſt the perſwaſion of their own minds, <hi>whether they will or not, comply they muſt.</hi> We ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver endeavoured ſuch driving forward
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:64952:37"/>work to bring any to an uniformity and ſubjection to that which we know of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to be according to the mind of God, and the counſel of his eternal Spirit, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentaneous or correſpondent to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Truth, or the true Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and no ways repugnant to, but congruous with the ſentiments of ſound Reaſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and its our deſire, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one ſhould be fully perſwaded in their own minds; and we direct them to wait upon the Lord, that he may reveal that to them which would tend to his glory and their good; and I know ſuch, who ſingly wait and are freely given up in an entire Reſignation to obey what God opens and commands, they will not want clearneſs nor freedom in their minds to follow that which is praiſe worthy, comely, and commendable in the ſight of the Lord and all ſober People; and then they will ſee (as many have come ſo to underſtand, who were once blinded and hardned alſo for a time, by the alluring ſnares and cunning ſtratagems of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my) and confeſs, that thoſe wholſom Counſels and weighty Admonitions from the Spirit of the Lord through his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, are not <hi>Preſcriptions</hi> and <hi>Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Men,</hi> or <hi>Innovations, Canons,</hi> &amp;c. as <hi>F. Bugg</hi> baſely inſinuates pag. 175. but
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:64952:38"/>that which is very profitable, yea, and neceſſary to prevent <hi>Looſneſs, Libertiniſm, Confuſion, Prophanity,</hi> and <hi>all manner of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery,</hi> which this ſelfiſh, diſorderly, ſeperate Spirit opens a door unto; and to keep down that ranting, rambling, wild, and wanton mind, that's got up in many, and matters not, nor will not bow to the good Diſcipline and heavenly Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And to ſhow thee, <hi>Reader,</hi> a little more of this vain Mans Impertinencies, he queries in an Iſhmaelitiſh Spirit, pag. 78. <hi>Then I ſtill further query of you Directory-makers</hi> (Dictator-like indeed, in an Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious manner) <hi>What's the reaſon, and what doth it mean, that neither</hi> Matthew, Mark, Luke, <hi>nor</hi> John, <hi>nor any one Chapter of any of thoſe Books are recorded in our <hi>Great Book of Records,</hi> firſt and before the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of</hi> G. F. <hi>as that which is more powerful, more binding, and of much more Authority?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What thinks thou, <hi>Reader,</hi> is not here a mighty fault committed? ſurely worthy of condign puniſhment, had he power to inflict it upon us; but I doubt much if he or others of his confuſed fraternity, would e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cape this imputation, notwithſtanding of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l their wiſdom, had they diſtinct Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly Meeting Books, to inſert in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of their great Books of Records,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:64952:38"/>either the Books or any one Chap. may be hardly ſo much as a ſingle verſe of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew, Mark, Luke,</hi> or <hi>John.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One may ſurely ſuppoſe this vain, idle man either miſſes of his prudentials, or elſe ſeems not to be in good earneſt and ſerious in what he ſcribles here and there.</p>
               <p>Thus, <hi>Reader,</hi> I have followed the Wiſemans advice, and in the middle way have kept, neither altogether on the one hand diſregarded theſe needleſs, ſenſleſs, Queries, and not to take no notice at all of them; nor to be too much concerned with them on the other hand, as to ſpend more time (and truly I think much more I have taken, than the Author or they ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſerve, and am almoſt wearied now in canvaſſing him, and tracing through his dirty puddles) and therefore it is ſaid, <hi>Anſwer not a fool according to his folly, leſt thou alſo be like unto him.</hi> (Here muſt be a holy ſlighting of the vain pratings and idle ſtories of ridiculous Fools) but then ſays the ſame Wiſeman, <hi>Anſwer a Fool according to his folly;</hi> and he gives the reaſon,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>As the phraſe is,</hi> Plus rogat aſinus, quam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iloſophus.</note> 
                  <hi>leſt he be wiſe in his own conceit.</hi> Oh would to God that the many ſeaſonable Anſwers had but this good effect upon thoſe <hi>Fools</hi> our preſent Antagoniſts and this peeviſh
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:64952:39"/>angry man <hi>F. B.</hi> amongſt the reſt, that he and they might ſeem no longer wiſe in their own conceits and imaginations, as this might tend to their unſpeakable mercy and laſting welfare; ſo alas! this is their great miſery, that comonly befalls theſe oppoſing, wilful, ſtubborn perſons, that inſtead of being bettered by due, correction, they (as ill-natured Boys, the more they are beat, the more croſs they are) they grow more obſtinate; or like to thoſe the Apoſtle mentions, <hi>Such as they are, even evil men and ſeducers, wax worſe and worſe, deceiving and being deceived; yea and whoſe latter end is worſe than the beginning:</hi> ſo that for my part I have but little hopes of theſe ſelf-conceited, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious, proud ones, who in their own fooliſh fancies imagine themſelves to be ſuch and ſuch, as its ſaid, <hi>Seeſt thou a man wiſe in his own conceit, there is more hope of a fool, than him.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>IN his IV. Chapter, pag. 87. in which he tranſcribes the <hi>Teſtmonies of</hi> R. H. F. H. <hi>with</hi> G. F's <hi>Old Doctrine and New Practice,</hi> &amp;c. as he calls it.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:64952:39"/>
               <p>Reader, I deſire thee to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice that it hath been the conſtant work of our Oppoſers to pervert and bring in one page or ſentence of Friends Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies which (as diſtinct by it ſelf, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out coherence and relation, either to what precedes, or what follows) may both ſeem to anſwer their crafty deſigns, and their malicious ends, and alſo claſh againſt the reſt of the matter not cited. Myſteries I do certainly know that they are not only miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtood and perverted with reſpect to what the Authors really meaned and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, but alſo miſ-applied by our Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers in this preſent matter.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">For I have obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>F. H</hi>'s Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny out of his Works in p. 614, 616, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> directly ſpeaking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and this <hi>F. B.</hi> brings in againſt Friends of Truth.</note>And as concerning the falſe ſuggeſtiion of this wicked, lying, perverſe man, that <hi>G. F</hi>'s new pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice were contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to his Old Doctrine, and ſeems to repeat <hi>W. R</hi>'s falſe, abuſive Charge of <hi>G. F</hi>'s being an Apoſtate and Innovator. For I do firmly believe that faithful, ancient Labourer of the Goſpel <hi>G. F.</hi> his teſtimony and practice now is not contrary to what he firſt preached; and the ſame almighty power and holy divine preſence that attended his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry in the beginning, continues with him
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:64952:40"/>now in his ſervices and exerciſes; and I do know that his life is hid with Chriſt in God: and let the Devil rage and roar, and his curſed inſtruments on every hand ſtamp and ſtare; yea, let the wicked bend their bow and ſhoot their arrows of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit and malice, the great God, the Lord Jehovah he will certainly ſurround us with his heavenly power, and over-ſhadow us with his divine wing, and protect us under his ſafe pavilion; whereby as we continue faithful to him, according to that good underſtanding he hath beſtowed upon us, and ſo retain our innocency and upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs before him, we ſhall be defended, and all our enemies confounded: For bleſſed be his holy name, that <hi>G. F.</hi> and many thouſands with him, know Chriſt Jeſus by his eternal ſpirit to rule in us, to be our Guide, our Head, our Law-giver, and who is made unto us of God, Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Righteouſneſs, Wiſdom, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
               <p>And as for thy bringing in the <hi>Profeſſors</hi> (pag. 99.) ſaying <hi>ſo and ſo,</hi> according to thy fooliſh invented ſtories and baſe lies, I know the ſober ſort of you and the very civil people of the world, will rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily acknowledg, and have done, when they have been witneſſes to our orderly Chriſtian way, in the beginning, proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:64952:40"/>and accompliſhing of our <hi>Marriages, that they have been really ſatisfied therewith, and that it was but lying ſlanders caſt upon us, that we did ſo and ſo, without regard either to God or Men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And further, Such alſo will condemn thee <hi>Francis</hi> and thy adherents, who in your haſty, forward, and raſh minds can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not wait in the patience to have your mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters done in that orderly diſcreet way and method amongſt the Lords people.</p>
               <p>And this brings before me, and which I cannot well omit, but take notice, how impudently thou inſinuates and ſlily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, <hi>That the way Friends take, were an ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie way and more pleaſing to the fleſh, and is moſt taking, and drawing after them the greateſt number; I ſpeak of them that profeſs the Truth:</hi> (ſee pag. 83.) Now let but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny rational and judicious perſon conſider in the firſt place, Whether that way is more eaſie and pleaſing to the fleſh, which leads people to a <hi>weighty ſerious deliberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of ſuch a great <hi>ſolemn Concern</hi> as <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage</hi> is, and ſo after their ponderous conſiderations to propoſe it before Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Friends both of Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens, and ſo to be ſatisfied in patience and ſubmiſſion of mind with the ordering hand of God, as they have Unity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and gives way to be accompliſhed,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:64952:41"/>which ſometimes as occaſion preſents, as circumſtances ſtand, and need is, may be pretty long betwixt the propoſal and accompliſhment: this I know has been ſo far from being an eaſie way and more pleaſing to the fleſh, that on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to ſeveral it hath proved a very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant, hard, and difficult exerciſe, to come before our publick Meetings, ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the way and order of Truth, and it has been in the croſs to their own wills; and they have got good by it both out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly and inwardly, though for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time it might ſeem tedious and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous to ſome.</p>
               <p>And next conſider Reader, Whether this way of <hi>Marriage</hi> be not indeed an eaſie and more pleaſing to the fleſh, for a man, after that his affections are drawn out towards a woman, immediately to give Friends a kind of a general ſlight notice thereof, may be after your publick Meetings, and tell them he intends to take ſuch a woman to be his wife; and ſo whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they have the conſent of Friends and their Unity therewith or not, they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, and in their minds fixed to go on and ſo in their own wills and at their own time, out of the fear of God and the good order of Truth, begins and ends their matter.</p>
               <p>And becauſe ſeveral diſorderly, haſty,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:64952:41"/>forward ſpirits could not have Friends at all to countenance them, they have run to the Prieſt and been married by him, and become either on the one hand looſe, yea and more wicked and extravagant in their debauched converſations than they were formerly, before they were convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of the Truth, or made profeſſion thereof, or on the other hand from the pride and prejudice of their minds, turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed diſaffected, and ſo joyned to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented oppoſite party; and as this was the very riſe or original cauſe, <hi>viz.</hi> either pride and prejudice in ſome, or looſeneſs and libertiniſm in others, that hath brought forth this curſed work of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration from and oppoſition to the Lord and his people, and which at laſt leads into <hi>Ranteriſm,</hi> yea <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net of prophanity; ſo its the very ſame this day that draws ſo many to joyn with theſe Separatiſts, and become their proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites; either ſuch I ſay as are from pride and prejudice diſaffected and diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or are inclinable to looſeneſs, wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and falſe liberty, and ſo ſuch grow weary of the Croſs, and cannot, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light not to walk longer in the ſtrait and narrow way of holineſs, that alone leads to everlaſting life. Thus that proverb is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled as to them, The Dog is turned to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:64952:42"/>his own vomit again, and the Sow that was waſhed to her wallowing in the mire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>AS concerning the V. and VI Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. wherein he inſerts the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſeveral of the <hi>Clergy</hi> both <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and ſhews the judgment of ancient <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and <hi>Martyrs,</hi> againſt <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions</hi> and <hi>forcing a Conformity to Mens Traditions not grounded on Scripture Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> &amp;c. We are not at all concerned with the wrong, abuſive application of theſe and divers other good teſtimonies of thoſe worthy men, the great tendency of all which, both what's cited by <hi>F. B.</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo much more could be produced, was to teſtifie againſt the Romiſh Antichriſtian Tyranny of Impoſing upon Tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences to be ſubject to their Superſtition and Idolatry, and of perſecuting and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting Temporal or Bodily Puniſhments upon ſuch as could not comply nor bow to them therein. See <hi>R. B</hi>'s <hi>Anarchy of the Ranters,</hi> &amp;c. that opens this very clearly.</p>
               <p>For though we do ſay, and always have
<pb facs="tcp:64952:42"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64952:43"/>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:64952:43"/>declared that forced Impoſition of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences is an Antichriſtian, Abominable, and Unreaſonable Practice: Yet we alſo affirm, according to the Scriptures of Truth, The true Church is to exert that Power and Authority with which ſhe is inveſted, and to improve that Priviledge God Almighty has beſtowed upon her in thoſe Admonitions, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> this in ſhort being more largely treated of by <hi>T. Ellwood,</hi> ſee his VI. Chap. in his <hi>Antidote,</hi> &amp;c. and other Friends, and alſo I direct thee to peruſe <hi>W. Gibſon</hi>'s General Epiſtle for the preſervation and increaſe of Charity and Unity, amongſt the Profeſſors of Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Printed and Sold by <hi>John Bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to return to the Matter in hand, Thou maiſt obſerve the height of Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Baſeneſs, and Malice in the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlative Degree in <hi>F. B.</hi> falſly inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting (in p. 115.) in his ungodly, lying, pretended Diſcovery of that Hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and two-fold Practice, <hi>Viz. Of plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng to the Magiſtrate for liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and at the ſame time are uſing and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing all force, rule, dominion, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, they are capable to inflict upon
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:64952:44"/>their diſſenting Brethren</hi> (thou ſheweſt thy ſelf here a to be an impudent lyar, that I muſt needs tell thee by the way) <hi>who cannot fall down and cry <hi>Hoſannah</hi> to every likeneſs</hi> (and here thou art an inſolent Scoffer) <hi>leſt the accepting and conforming to one needleſs Ceremony, ſhould be ground of encouragement to the Ruling Party, to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce another, and ſo a numberleſs number, until at length <hi>Rome</hi> may (if poſſible) be out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reader,</hi> I cannot but ſignifie to thee that we are not unſenſible what the main Deſign is of all this ſad, grievous, work of Unchriſtian Defamations, baſe, lying, Reflections, and groundleſs Suggeſtions, as if we were endeavouring to <hi>impoſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on tender Conſciences,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Perſecu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſuch as will not Conform, and be in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity;</hi> this I ſay is the very Work of the Devil, to expoſe an innocent, harmleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> People, to the hard Cenſures, ſever<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Thoughts, and ſtrange Apprehenſions o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them, and not only ſo, but to be an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of ambage to the cruel maliciou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Perſecutors, both to harden them i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their work, and alſo to inſtigate others whoſe inclination leads them not thereto So thou maiſt eaſily diſcern what is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tendency of this deviliſh Work of <hi>Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:64952:44"/>to the Heavenly Government of Chriſt, eſtabliſhed in and amongſt his People,</hi> and what Spirit it is that drives and hurries them on joyned thereunto; no doubt but that it is a <hi>murdering</hi> one (even that of <hi>Cain,</hi> and that of <hi>Rabſhakeh,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding its fair pretences, as if it were for <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> againſt <hi>Impoſitions, Preſcriptions,</hi> and <hi>Innovations</hi> of Men, and ſo ſeem to be <hi>for the Lord,</hi> as he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended; <hi>Am I now come</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>without the Lord againſt this place to deſtroy it? The Lord ſaid to me</hi> (here was a great boaſt) <hi>Go up againſt this Land, and deſtroy it,</hi> &amp;c. Yet good <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekias</hi> ſaid, <hi>This is a day of Trouble, of Rebuke, of Blaſphemy,</hi> when the King of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> had ſent this <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the living God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.25.19.3. which would not only be contented to ſtain our Reputations amongſt ſober people, but alſo labours by theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct means, that we might be in hazard of being deprived both of our <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Eſtates,</hi> in falſly and moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly rendring of us as <hi>Papiſts, Apoſtates, Innovators,</hi> and <hi>Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well <hi>Francis,</hi> we leave the God of Heaven to reckon with thee for all thy
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:64952:45"/>
                  <hi>Helliſh Lies, Slanders,</hi> and <hi>Inſinuations,</hi> and we deſire thou may'ſt find a place of Repentance.</p>
               <p>In thy 7th. Chap p. 128. I find little of weight in it to be noticed by me, in reſpect that the ſubſtance of the matter therein contained, for the moſt part re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to particular perſons by <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Onely amongſt ſome of thy Queries I ſhall obſerve thy 6th, in p. 158. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou asks, <hi>Whether it be not a <hi>Popiſh Tenet</hi> to cry down Wiſdom, and to ſay that Wiſdom will deſtroy us, as it is uſual with you to ſay?</hi> (And then comparing us with the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> goes on) <hi>for the</hi> Papiſts <hi>can not how fooliſh the common people are, not how much in Ignorance (it being, as they ſay, the Mother of Devotion) they edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate them; provided their Miniſters an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Jeſuits be very expert and able to defen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> their way of Worſhip, and heap of Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies: And when do any that Write or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute to defend our way of Worſhip,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> Its well known how great Fools and Ideots the blind World hath ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted and reckoned us to be in our Speaking or Writing to defend the true VVay and VVorſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Write on Speak like Fools, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they can neithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Write nor Speak other ways? And why do yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cry out againſt Wiſdom
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:64952:45"/>upon every occaſion; as if Ignorance were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come our only Darling.</hi> Thus far <hi>F. B.</hi> in his Query.</p>
               <p>And his Anſwer is with the words of <hi>W. P</hi>'s Addreſs to Proteſtants (p. 187.) end as he abuſes this paſſage with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in his Book, perverting them by miſapplications to a wrong uſe, never, I know, intended by the Author, to grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie this evil, malicious Spirit, and its a pity that ſuch a good Book that has been of ſo great a Service, ſhould be thus abuſed; and I cannot paſs by, but deſire, <hi>VV. P.</hi> may take notice of this twofold Practice of this deceitful, hypocritical Perſon, who ſometimes ſeems to admire and fawn upon him, when he expreſſes himſelf thus in (p. 133.) <hi>Now let us a little Animadvert upon this <hi>Noblemans words,</hi> viz. VV. P</hi>'s and yet at other times ſeems baſely to abuſe and indirectly Reflects upon him (as in p. 145.) ſaying to <hi>VV. P. That they may not look one way, and row another, a thing ſome ſuſpect</hi> (may be thy ſelf as ready as any, for all thou ſeems to be clear of ſuch a ſuſpicion) <hi>by thy diſputing on</hi> G. F's. <hi>part,</hi> &amp;c. But as to what the Queries ſay, <hi>VVhy do we cry out againſt VViſdom on every occaſion,</hi> &amp;c. he either is a very <hi>Ignora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> of that Wiſdom againſt which we do
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:64952:46"/>thus cry, otherwiſe he would not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſuch an impertinent Query; or elſe its from a malicious premeditated Deſign, contrived from his carnal fleſhly Wiſdom (as I rather judge) to amuſe ſimple peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and beget a wrong Apprehenſion in their Minds of our <hi>oneneſs with the Papiſts</hi> in this point.</p>
               <p>For its well known, that we never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied that Wiſdom and Underſtanding which cometh down from above, that's heavenly, pure, peaceable, and gentle, eaſie to be intreated, wherewith God endows his people, to diſcern and ſee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all bad, dark, and oppoſite Spirits in all their twinings and twiſtings from the earthly, carnal Wiſdom that's from below, deviliſh and ſenſual, which hath begot in the hearts of thoſe who are led by it, bitter envy and ſtrife; and as the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>Where this is</hi> (as we may obſerve by daily experience on every hand) <hi>Confuſion, and every evil work is amongst them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Teſtimony ſtands againſt this ſort of <hi>Natural Wiſdom,</hi> unſubjected to the holy divine power, and therefore hear what the Wiſe Man ſaith unto thee, who cries up ſo much the ſame, <hi>Ceaſe from thy own Wiſdom,</hi> Pro. 23.4. and ſee how much the Apoſtle ſpeaks againſt this Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:64952:46"/>Citing the Prophets words, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.14. <hi>For it is written, I will deſtroy the <hi>Wisdom</hi> of the <hi>Wiſe,</hi> &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>where is the Wiſe, the Scribe, the Diſputer of this World? Hath not God made fooliſh the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom thereof, and the World by Wiſdom knew not God:</hi> 1 Cor. 1. (nor to this day doth the World by its Wiſdom know him) <hi>and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren ye ſee your Calling, how that not many Wiſe men after the Fleſh are called:</hi> But we know that there is a Divine Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and heavenly Wiſdom better than ſtrength, and better than Weapons, and it is the lowly that feels this Wiſdom to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in and remain with them, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the Lord there are a remnant who have ſupplicated before him, not for <hi>Riches, Honour, Wealth, nor Long life,</hi> but with the Wiſe King, <hi>Give us Wiſdom and Knowledg,</hi> and he hath granted this our Requeſt; O magnified be his moſt Holy Reverend Name for ever and for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
               <p>In p. 211. he brings in another buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs concerning the Order of <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> which <hi>VV. R.</hi> makes a great noiſe about in his buſtling bulkſome Book, that's a heap of <hi>Lies</hi> and <hi>Conſuſion;</hi> but they have no ſuch reaſon, conſidering in the firſt place, that if they did that which was not
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:64952:47"/>agreeable to Truth, ſhould be a juſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to impeach a Body of people as guilty thereof: I deſire they may learn bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the right Rule of Reaſoning of Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; for any perſon of ſmall judgment may conceive it were unreaſonable to conclude, becauſe that <hi>F. B.</hi> may be of ſuch a heady, wilful, croſs, perverſe Nature, or that <hi>W. R.</hi> may be of ſuch a high, ſelf-conceited, violent, oppoſite Spirit, therefore that all who are inclinable to follow or favour him a little in his Curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Work of Diviſion, are ſo malicious and envious, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as he or <hi>F. B.</hi> are.</p>
               <p>And Secondly, I believe Friends at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> have diſproved in that particular a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid.</p>
               <p>But Laſtly, If thoſe belonging to that Meeting were all contented with, and gave their conſents to that Order, from divers Conſiderations, inducing them thereto; here I think then was no impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or forcing in the matter relating particularly to themſelves, though it was an Error which they themſelves have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, as <hi>R. R.</hi> hath fully ſhewn in his Anſwer to <hi>T. C.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what will not wrong minded Men catch advantage againſt, and raiſe jang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and contention about!</p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:64952:47"/>
               <p>I cannot paſs by, but diſcover to thee Reader a little more of this railing, abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Mans Temper, <hi>F. B.</hi> who in p. 178. moſt baſely Calumniates and falſly Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that precious worthy Servant of the Lord <hi>G. W.</hi> at a moſt unworthy, uncivil rate, ſaying, <hi>He being lately in</hi> Hunting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonſhire <hi>and elſe where, where he took too much upon him, and behaved himſelf more like a Lordly Biſhop or Popiſh Prelate, than an humble Miniſter of Chriſt; and by me at this time is, and ſtands impeached, as an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> a <hi>Vſurper over the Conſcience,</hi> the which I ſtand ready publickly to Aſſert, Maintain, and Vindicate;</hi> and in p. 39. in his ſcoffing ſtrain ſays, (Citing the words of the <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer of the Brethren</hi>) <hi>we do profeſs ſeriouſly</hi> (<hi>a notable ſerious</hi> George, <hi>if we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him</hi>) ſaith <hi>F. B.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I deſire the Reader to peruſe the ſaid Book, which he ſuppoſes <hi>G. VV.</hi> to be the Author of; and he ſhall find both him and Friends finally Vindicated from theſe foul wicked Villanies, baſe and lying Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and though its well known gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally amongſt Friends that <hi>G. W.</hi> is of a tender, mild, and meek Spirit, and there needs little to be ſaid to Vindicate his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, his Honeſly, and Fidelity
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:64952:48"/>being ſo apparent and noted amongſt us; yet meeting with a Certificate from Friends in <hi>Huntingtonſhire,</hi> I was willing to inſert it.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <dateline>From our Monthly Meeting at <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moncheſter,</hi> 
                           <date>the 7th of the 5th Month, 1682.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </opener>
                     <p>WHereas <hi>George VVhitehead</hi> hath beeen evilly traduced in two Letters of <hi>Fra. Buggs,</hi> and charged in one of them, with behaving himſelf in <hi>Huntingtonſhire</hi> like a <hi>Lordly Biſhop</hi> or <hi>Popiſh Prelate</hi> lately. Now we whoſe Names are ſubſcribed, do teſtifie, That we never in this County, nor elſewhere at any time, ſaw any ſuch thing: And that he is a Man of a temper remote from any ſuch matter, but do believe he is a true Labourer in Godd Service, and an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Matth. Key</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Samuel Notinghon</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Tobias Hardmeat</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Robert Liſter</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Jaſper Robins</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>John Wilsford</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>John Devenſol</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>VVill. Starling</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Rd. Snahdall</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>John King</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>David Tiſdal</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Tho. Liſter</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <note n="*" place="bottom">VVhoſe Name <hi>F.B.</hi> ſets down in his Book <hi>in p. 98.</hi> approving ſomething ſent to the Quarterly Meeting in the Iſle of <hi>Ely,</hi> in which he ſays abuſively <hi>(but grieved ſome Friends)</hi> and addeth this his Forgery in a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentheſis, [perhaps <hi>Richard Jobſon</hi> and <hi>Tobias Hardmeat,</hi> G. Foxes <hi>two principal Studs in that Country.</hi>]</note> 
                                 <hi>Richard Jobſon.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:64952:48"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> A Catalogue of the Scoffing Lyes, and Scandalous, Abuſive Inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations from <hi>F. B's Second Part,</hi> conſiſting of falſe Matter, placed on a wrong Subject, and tending to a bad end.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>IN page 4. he falſly Inſinuates,</hi> That their way (intending <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c.) of compelling, and antichriſtian way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding to bring to, and force an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity, is by us ſlighted and contemned.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>II. (p. 6.) He ſays,</hi> And how far theſe Tyrannical proceedings have been uſed by our new Spiritual Lords.</p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:64952:49"/>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>III. (P. 8.)</hi> And now I will ſhew a Paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell betwixt the Treatments which the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> met with from the hands of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> for their <hi>pains,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">An odious Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon.</note> and betwixt the Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that <hi>W. R<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> T. C.</hi> and others have met withal from the hands of <hi>G. F.</hi> and thoſe of party with him, for their pains, and I expect no better reward; for I know they will be very angry, yea dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful angry, to ſee their <hi>Rood of Grace,</hi> or <hi>Graceleſs,</hi> as well as <hi>Lifeleſs Image <hi>[Note a graceleſs as well as lifeleſs Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on]</hi>
                  </hi> brought forth to the peoples view in its proper dreſs, in all its imperfect parts, ana deformed ſhapes, as I have done, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſeveral ſorts of Mettals it is made up with, and the ill compoſed Ingredients therewith tempered to make it ſtand; when all is done, it is ſo lame of its Feet, and ſo benummed to the Toes end, that it muſt and will fall as ſoon as ever Implicit Faith; and Blind Obedience [the <hi>Papiſts</hi> old Crutches] do but take away their hands from it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Francis, <hi>I tell thee, unleſs thou un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feignedly repent of this thy baſe, ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous, treacherous work of Folly, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and Mockery, of theſe envious Suggeſtions, ſcurrilous Reflections, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Abuſes and Perverſions of thy
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:64952:49"/>Scoffing, Railing, and Reviling; remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber I warn thee of it, a moſt terrible dreadful reward may thou expect and look for to meet with from the hand of the Righteous Judge of all Fleſh, and which unavoidably ſhall overtake thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>IV. P. 59.</hi> We cry to the Magiſtrates for the liberty and the free exerciſe of our Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences in Matters Spiritual; and will not, nay reſolves not, come what will come, to allow the free Exerciſe of Conſcience in Matters Spiritual, to our Diſſenting Brethren. [<hi>A falſhood; we allow the ſame Liberty we call for,</hi> i. e. <hi>from Corporal Puniſhments,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but not from Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Goſpel Reproofs.</hi>]</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>V. P. 71.</hi> The whole Rubrick, Laws, and Canons Eccleſiaſtical of <hi>G. F.</hi> and other Innovators — they have no will to reaſon things, to debate things; but too much like the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> would have things taken up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Truſt. [Note, <hi>theſe are abominable-Lies upon Lies, and moſt odious Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; and he is a lying Informer that is the Author of them.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>VI. P. 75.</hi> And in as much as you ſeem to make <hi>G. F.</hi> the Author of the Errors, it ſtands him upon, finally to reject, and to bear a publick Teſtimony againſt the new ſtrange and dangerous Innovations and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byloniſh
<pb facs="tcp:64952:50"/>Inventions. — In whoſe Name you compleat a Conformity to the new Invent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Orders and Rules, under pain of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. <hi>[Theſe are all Clamorous A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes, and Slanderous Aſperſions, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Proofs.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>VII. And p. 83.</hi> Drawing them from the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing within</hi> to <hi>Obſervations with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out,</hi> to expreſs the Kingdom there, being an eaſie way, and more pleaſing to the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> is moſt taking, drawing after them the greateſt number: I ſpeak of them that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Truth. <hi>[The Charge is general and Abuſive.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>VIII. P. 95. Speaking of</hi> G.F. <hi>ſaith,</hi> And if <hi>W. R.</hi> calls him <hi>Apoſtate</hi> and <hi>Innovator,</hi> as that he is manifeſt enough to be, then he is angry, and thoſe of party with him ſtigma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize and abuſe <hi>W. R.</hi> inſtead of endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to convince <hi>G. F.</hi> of the Error of his way. [Note, <hi>what abuſe of</hi> W. R? <hi>and what Errors,</hi> &amp;c.]</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>IX. And p. 95. <hi>Antichriſtian Canons,</hi>
                  </hi> which limit people to a Stated Form. <hi>[A ſoul Slander again, yet we muſt hold the Form of Godlineſs, though Ranters op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>X. P. 97.</hi> To cover their Deceit and Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and Arbitrary Church Government, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, Lordſhip, <hi>&amp;c. [All groſs Slanders.]</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:64952:50"/>
               <p n="11">
                  <hi>XI. And page 102.</hi> But you deny the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Chriſt and his Apoſtles to be<note place="margin">n="*" A Lye.</note> A Rule; and yet we ſee you are for A Rule as much as any People: only you muſt have a Rule of your own Making, of your own Framing; a Child of your own Brain muſt be your Darling — And ſo make to your ſelves a Graven Image. <hi>[This is not true of the people called Quakers, but of thy ſelf, and ſuch as thou art.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">
                  <hi>XII. P. 115, 116. he ſaith,</hi> — To diſcover that Hypocritical and Two-faced Practice, <hi>viz.</hi> Of pleading to the Magiſtrate for Liberty of Conſcience, and at the ſame time are uſing and exerciſing all Force, Rule, Dominion, and Authority they are capable to inflict upon their Brethren, who cannot fall down, and cry <hi>HOSANNA</hi> to every Likeneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>[How loathſome is</hi> F.B. <hi>heaping up ſuch a Dunghil of lyes!]</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">
                  <hi>XIII. And (p. 150, 151, 152, 153.) In a Letter of his to</hi> G.W. <hi>he thus ſaith,</hi> It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported that <hi>Nicholas Lucas</hi> told thee, <hi>THOU WENTEST UP AND DOWN TO CHEAT THE COUNTRY;</hi> [I reckon he meant not of Money, but the people of their Liberty they have right to.] Truly thy Behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our hath manifeſted the Truth of his words in a great meaſure, as I am abbe to make appear not only by thy Advice in <hi>Huntingtonſhire;</hi> but alſo by thy Erronious Doctrine amongſt us,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:64952:51"/>&amp;c. — <hi>Exerciſe Dominion,</hi> Gentile-<hi>like, over your Brethren; as if you were reſolved to turn</hi> Monopolizers, <hi>and</hi> Ingroſſers <hi>of all Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Rule and Dominion over Conſciences into your hands</hi>—<hi>Oh! the Diſcord, Contention and Debate, which entered, and doth daily increaſe by reaſon of the Ceremonies, and your forced Conformity to them: and the chief cauſe hereof lies at your Doors.</hi> [See the Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficate from Friends of <hi>Huntingtonſhire</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted p. 90. which ſufficiently detects his Abuſes, and Defamations againſt <hi>G. W.</hi>]</p>
               <p n="14">XIV. And in p. 164. he thus inſinuates, <hi>viz. Whereby we thwart and contradict our avowed Principles; and ſo are building again the thing we once deſtroyed and cryed out againſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning in others the things we allow in our ſelves. Through which Practices a man may diſcern, without a pair of Spectacles,</hi> ERROUR and SUPERSTITION <hi>coming in apace;</hi> LIMPING upon the <hi>old Crutches of</hi> IMPLICITE FAITH and BLIND OBEDIENCE. [What are thoſe he thus accuſeth? The people called Quakers are not chargeable herewith.]</p>
               <p n="15">XV. And in page 159. he thus inſinuates, <hi>When do any that write or diſpute, to defend our way of Worſhip, write and ſpeak like</hi> Fools, <hi>except they can neither write nor ſpeak other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe? and why do you cry out againſt</hi> Wiſdom <hi>upon every accaſion? as if</hi> Ignorance <hi>were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:64952:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>our only</hi> Darling. [This is an <hi>abominable abuſe:</hi> we cry out againſt no Wiſdom, but cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, fleſhly, earthly, ſenſual, deviliſh Wiſdom]</p>
               <p n="16">XVI. P. 163. George Fox, <hi>See if thou haſt not as much need of a battledore as the Schollars and Profeſſors had,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">n="*" A Groſs Lye.</note> 
                  <hi>who art as much</hi> APOSTATIZED <hi>from thy former Principles for liberty of Conſcience as the Schollars and Profeſſors were from the ſingle Language, viz.</hi> THEE <hi>and</hi> THOU <hi>to a ſingle perſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And a little after he brings in this abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive lye and wicked Inſinuation in rhime, viz.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>This I ſet here, not to Adore</l>
                  <l>Becauſe I do well underſtand,</l>
                  <l>He that gave forth the battle-dore</l>
                  <l>Now brings Grapes of another Land;</l>
                  <l>Which ſower be, becauſe not free</l>
                  <l>From Force and Impoſitions;</l>
                  <l>Although as yet he will not ſee</l>
                  <l>Them like old Romes Traditions.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Think'ſt to ſcare us out of our good Order with thy <hi>Goggle-eyed Image</hi> of <hi>Jealouſie:</hi> which if thou didſt ſee through thy own Spectacles might affright thee out of thy ſhallow Conceits. An ugly Spectacle. For,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rogers, Criſp, Pennyman, Bullock</hi> and <hi>Bugg,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Dark Devil-driven Dungy-gods deſp rately lug,</l>
                  <l>That are ty'd to the tail of their ſeparate Schiſm</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pap-Lihertin-Heathen-Juda-Athe-iſm.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:64952:52"/>
               <p n="17">XVII. And pag. 178. Speaking of <hi>Richard Richardſon,</hi> he thus Scoſſingly inſinuates, viz. <hi>If</hi> R. R. <hi>hath no better</hi> Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick, <hi>he need not be admir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by</hi> G. W. <hi>in print for his great Learning,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See R. R. Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients againſt the Venom in W. <hi>R</hi> s. Book Printed for John Bringhurſt.</note> 
                  <hi>nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps had not, only he hath found out ſome</hi> Hiſtory, <hi>or</hi> Popiſh <hi>Author</hi> (This is a lye; for there are many Proteſtant Authors) <hi>which ſay,</hi> There were Deaconneſſes, as well as Deacons: <hi>which were helpful to</hi> G. W. <hi>in his preaching and diſputing for</hi> Womens Meetings <hi>lately in</hi> Huntingtonſhire, <hi>and elſewhere; where he took too much upon him, &amp; behaved himſelf more like a</hi> Lordly Biſhop <hi>or</hi> Popiſh Prelate, <hi>than an</hi> humble Miniſter <hi>of Chriſt.</hi> [This is confuted before.]</p>
               <p n="18">XVIII. Pa 195. <hi>And now I ſhall turn to the Biſhops of the</hi> Proteſtant-Churches, <hi>and do not queſtion, but ſhall make it appear, that they (their Power conſidered, and that the Laws are on their ſides) are more moderate, and uſe not that Severity to the Members of their Church (although they are ſevere enough too) that</hi> George Fox, <hi>and thoſe of party with him, uſe to the poor</hi> QUAKERS, <hi>if they chance to tranſgreſs their Traditions, &amp;c.</hi> [Theſe are falſe and proofleſs inſinuations.]</p>
               <p n="19">XIX. And in p. 200. <hi>They do not only teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy againſt that</hi> BAD SPIRIT, <hi>as they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:64952:52"/>it, but</hi> HIM ALSO, <hi>viz, the</hi> MAN ALSO: <hi>Oh! that we could but ſay,</hi> TAKE HIM GOALER, <hi>and that effectually.</hi> [A wicked Lye and baſe Inſinuation.]</p>
               <p n="20">XX. And in p. 291. he hath this abuſive Scoff, viz. <hi>For which very piece of</hi> Service, Stamp <hi>and</hi> Probatum eſt, <hi>I think that very Meeting deſerves a</hi> TRIPPLE CROWN. [For this thou <hi>F. B.</hi> deſerves to be reputed a Scornfull Lying Informer.]</p>
               <p n="21">XXI. Page 208. <hi>And now may they</hi> [the Presbyterians,] <hi>ſay to</hi> G. F. <hi>What hadſt thou rather that</hi> B. Clark <hi>and</hi> J. Bringhurſt, <hi>ſhould ſell</hi> Papiſts-<hi>Books,</hi> Play-<hi>Books,</hi> Jeſting-<hi>Books,</hi> nay <hi>Books, rather than that Book of</hi> W.R. [What <hi>Papiſts books are theſe? Prophane books we own not,</hi> mark that; and then brings in this lye for the reaſon of their not Selling it] <hi>becauſe it Diſcovers the Naked Truth of their</hi> NEW MODEL OF CHURCH GOVERNMENT. [But <hi>J. B.</hi> gives a Conſcientious Reaſon to the Reader, at the beginning of <hi>Chr. Taylors Epiſtle of Caution; &amp;c.</hi> why he could not fell them. And we teſtifie againſt Play-books, Jeſting-books, Popiſh-books, and diſown the ſelling of them, as we do the ſelling <hi>W. R's</hi> and thine, for they are all from one ſpirit, only yours the moſt malicious and leſs to be born, becauſe of your hypocritical pretended Friendſhip. See <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 55.12, 13.]</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:64952:53"/>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <p>IN this following Chapter I ſhall inſert what the ſenſe of J. S. and J. W. is concerning <hi>Womens-meetings,</hi> and alſo what T. C. ſayes in his <hi>Babels,</hi> part 1ſt. page 9. with a paper ſubſcribed by <hi>Iohn Wilkinſon,</hi> and others of his party, approving of and unanimouſly conſenting to the Epiſtle of G. F. which F. B. terms <hi>his new order</hi> (which was wrote about the year 1671) <hi>for womens Meetings;</hi> all which contradicts F. B. in his violent Rage, and moſt furious Claſhings againſt <hi>Womens Meetings,</hi> as the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing impartial <hi>Reader</hi> may readily perceive by his peruſing of the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt, John Wilkinſon</hi>'s and <hi>John Story</hi>'s Senſe concerning <hi>Womens Meetings.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>As we do approve of Monthly and Quarterly meetings, for the neceſſary ſervice of the Truth; ſome ſay, that as theſe or any other meetings of Friends in Truth, ſhall be continued to anſwer thoſe ſervices, we believe that as it now is, it alſo will become our
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:64952:53"/>duty to be at unity with our brethren in the ſervice thereof; and though one of us (viz. <hi>J. Wilkinſon</hi>) did condiſcend to ſubſcribe a paper for the erecting a womans meeting in the Country, to anſwer the ends propoſed in the paper, which (he teſtifies.) he then did in ſingleneſs of heart for unitys ſake: yet according to that inward ſence we now have, there appears to us no abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute neceſſity to continue <hi>Womens meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> in the Country diſtinct and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from the men, and therefore do conſcientiouſly forbear to aſſent or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage to lay the Intentions of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage before them; yet that inward ſence and heavenly underſtanding we receive from God, hath and yet doth confirm us in this Judgment, that it's not agreeable with the line of Truth, to oppoſe others in the Exerciſe and appointed ſervice of the ſaid Meetings as heretofore and yet ſetled and agreed upon, who being conſcious therein, are <hi>otherwiſe minded</hi> than we are; &amp; if any of our <hi>words</hi> &amp; <hi>actions</hi> have any tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to oppoſe, &amp;c. (which we are not
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:64952:54"/>conſcious of, but if we were, we would readily confeſs,) we ſay the Truth in us would have condemned it, even as it now doth; and if it ſhall pleaſe the Lord to manifeſt unto us a ſervice in thoſe Meetings in the Country as well as Citys, the ſame integrity towards God, which hath dwelt with us this many years paſt, we believe will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Bond on us to joyn <hi>Hand</hi> and <hi>Heart</hi> with others our Brethren and Siſters therein; but till then our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires are, that they may not become an occaſion of ſtraitneſs of Spirit each to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards others, but that embracing the wholeſome Council of the Apoſtle in another caſe, <hi>If in any thing ye are otherwiſe minded, wait till God reveal it;</hi> we may walk together in pure unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed love of our God, which thinketh no Evill.</q>
               <p>This I have from <hi>T. C's</hi> Book, called, <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Teſtimonys concerning Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> page 23. the ſame alſo is ſet down at large in <hi>W. R's</hi> Book, 4 part, page 37. which we ſuppoſe he has abbreviated out of it.</p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:64952:54"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> But that which more cloſely contradicts <hi>F. B.</hi> hear what <hi>T. C.</hi> his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Iniquity ſaith in the 9'th page of his <hi>Babels,</hi> part 1ſt.</p>
               <q>Now thoſe they term STUB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BORN, are not againſt Men and Womens Meetings, but differ about the form and power thereof, they are only againſt Women having Meetings <hi>apart from the men,</hi> when they have <hi>no buſineſs</hi> requires it; not againſt them in Citys, Great Towns, and Places, where they live near together, &amp; occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons require; but where they live <hi>remote</hi> from each other, and have no Buſineſs; alſo the form of Marriages, &amp;c. (for theſe perſons who they ſay are againſt Meetings, do and are willing to uſe them on neceſſary occaſions,) this is the great State of the Difference, and Caſe of thoſe Perſons <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. terms <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> bad <hi>Spirits, &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>G.F.</hi> &amp;c. ſay, The Univerſal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit cannot receive that.</q>
               <p>Thus far <hi>T. C.</hi> fairly grants: from which 1ſt. obſerve, They declare, or <hi>T. C.</hi> on their behalf, <hi>that they are not againſt Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:64952:55"/>Meetings, and that they are only againſt Womens Meetings apart from the Men, when they have no buſineſs;</hi> which grants they are for them when they have buſineſs even to be apart from the Men though they ſay there is no Precept, Preſident nor Command for them in Scriptures; and who ſhould be the moſt proper Judges of the Buſineſs? I hope they'l grant, that thoſe who are moſt immediately concerned to do the buſineſs muſt judge when they have buſineſs, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> They declare, or <hi>T. C.</hi> for them, <hi>that they are not againſt Womens Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings diſtinct or apart from the Men, in City's, Great Towns and Places;</hi> and yet Cry out againſt, without diſtinction, ſcoffing at them, and calling them <hi>a Dead Lifeleſs Image,</hi> and comparing them to the <hi>Rood of Grace,</hi> (ſo called) &amp;c. that <hi>F. B.</hi> ſaith, <hi>would ſmile when a good gift was given it, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They <hi>are only againſt Womens Meetings where they live remote from each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; have no buſineſs; but if they have buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs then they may meet.</hi> He doth not ſay, they muſt bring Chapter and Verſe for their meeting at the tenth hour of the day, to get a little ſtock, &amp;c. no, no; if they have but <hi>buſineſs, they may meet,</hi> ſaith <hi>T. C.</hi> though there is neither Precept, Preſident nor Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for them, I will diſpenſe with that in Cities, great Towns and places, nay in
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:64952:55"/>Counties too, if they have buſineſs,) and then I hope if there be need they'l grant they may meet when they be found in the practice of communicating and doing good, which the Apoſtle ſaith is that Sacrifice wherewith the Lord is well pleaſed, as alſo to viſit (and communicate where need is) the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs and the Widow, and not be like to thoſe the Apoſtle mentions; <hi>If a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or Siſter be naked and deſtitute of day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly food, and one of you ſay unto them, depart in peace, be you warmed and filled, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ye give them not thoſe things which are needfull to the body, Ja.</hi> 2 16. And if they have a ſtock for theſe Chriſtian Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Uſes it matters not what the Devil, envious or hard-hearted men &amp; women may ſay, that may have of this Worlds goods, and yet ſuffer your Brothers and Siſters, or the poor Fatherleſs and diſtreſſed to want, for theſe Cannot truly ſay with good <hi>Job,</hi> 31.16, 17. <hi>verſ. If I have withheld the poor from their deſire, or have Cauſed the Eyes of the Widow to fail, or have eaten my mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell alone, and the Fatherleſs have not eaten thereof: If I have ſeen any periſh for want of Cloathing, or any poor without Covering? If his loines have not bleſſed me; and if he were not warmed with the fleece of my ſheep, &amp;c. Then let my arm fall from my ſhoulder-blade,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:64952:56"/>and mine arm be broken from the bone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So by what <hi>T. C.</hi> writes it is over and over granted, that the women may meet apart from the men. So that one may tell <hi>F. B.</hi> that <hi>T. C.</hi> (whoſe Babells he quotes) grants what he ſpends many pages againſt: And Prints a fooliſh nonſenſical Ballad of ſcorn againſt, (to which is added many verſes that were not in the former,) and this ſaith <hi>T. C.</hi> is the great part of the difference and the caſe of thoſe perſons <hi>G. F.</hi> terms Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, &amp;c. <hi>viz.</hi> in ſhort, that they are only for womens meetings when there is buſineſs and neceſſary occaſions, &amp;c. Well, if they can produce when or where any women had their meeting and no buſineſs, nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary occaſion, let them, and then prove that its a Crime at ſuch times to wait upon the Lord in his Spirit and fear, to receive of his Divine Counſel and Wiſdom, by which they may be acted and guided to the praiſe of his Grace, to ſhew forth the vertues of him that hath called them, &amp;c. and that <hi>that</hi> is not a neceſſary occaſion. And furthermore obſerve, we have mens monthly meetings, and muſt they not meet at the time appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed if no buſineſs ſhould preſent? And if they meet not, pray how ſhould they know whether they have buſineſs or not? And if they may meet, why not the women like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe? If neither, except as before, why
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:64952:56"/>is any time appointed? This looks as if they would have Friends only meet when they can tell of outward buſineſs to be propoſed; ſo if any but ſay, he knows no buſineſs, he is excuſed. Oh what a diſorder and confuſion would they lead into! Well may they be termed <hi>Babell's-builders,</hi> and compared to the fooliſh woman, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3<hi rend="sup">ly.</hi> Moreover Reader, I deſire thee to conſider that notwithſtanding <hi>F. B.</hi> ſo much abuſes that Epiſtle of <hi>G. F</hi>'s concerning Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens meetings, which he tranſcribes in <hi>p.</hi> 33. and brings in as a proof of an alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and violence done to our firſt Principles of union, whereof I have already taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice: See Chap. IV. p. 50. Yet this very ſame paper was approved of by <hi>John Wilkin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and others of his party, and for thy fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſatisfaction, and to ſhew thee both how much they have contradicted this fooliſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited man <hi>F. B.</hi> and likewiſe thou mayſt clearly ſee how much they are degenerated, and Apoſtatized from what they once own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, I ſhall preſent a paper writ from the Quarterly meeting at <hi>Kendall</hi> the 6th of 8th month 1671. where the foreſaid Epiſtle of <hi>G. F</hi>'s. was read and joyned with, and with an unanimous Conſent to be Practiſed, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by what follows.</p>
               <q>It is further agreed upon, that this pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per be read in every particular Meeting
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:64952:57"/>that the <hi>WOMEN-friends,</hi> who are faithful, may be ſtirred up to a ſerious conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the <hi>light</hi> of the Lord, to examin them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and feel his requirings, and ſo to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Lord with diligence and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of mind, that ſo every one that profeſs the living truth of God may be ſerviceable Inſtruments in his hand to Extol his Name, and to perfect his praiſe in our day and time. And in the womens aſſembling together, to ſee and conſider that all women, young and old, who profeſs the Truth, do walk there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in in good order, in modeſty and moderation, in Charity, out of the Cuſtoms &amp; faſhions of the World, and that nothing be lacking; and ſo herein the femals will become very ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the neceſſities of the body, and ſo you will rejoyce with them that do rejoyce, and ſuffer with them that do ſuffer, and mourn with them that do mourn, who are not got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten out of the bondage and Captivity of the adverſary, and ſo be ready to lend unto ſuch a helping hand, and encourage every ſuch good deſire, and reprove the willful and obſtinate. And ſo every one acting in the juſt Principle of God in our ſelves juſtice will be exalted, and righteouſneſs eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and herein <hi>Male</hi> and <hi>Female</hi> is ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in our <hi>place</hi> and calling in this our day &amp; generation: And ſo all <hi>Women-Friends</hi> who
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:64952:57"/>feel ſincere deſires in themſelves to be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental of good unto others, let them meet together (as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid<note place="margin">n="*" <hi>viz</hi> as is expreſſed in <hi>G. F</hi>'s paper, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in its found thus; &amp; ſo it would do well for the Women to have a diſtinct meeting? by themſelves, as it is in other places, and to ſee that nothing be lacking— So once a month to have a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans meeting in the County-Town, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places convenient then the other Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Women may come &amp; go home they meeting together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the 10th hour of the day, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note>) and in this deſire certainly the Lord will aſſiſt you in his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Counſel to act &amp; ſpeak that which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient; and all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful women who are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined and affected here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with may ſignifie their minds and intents to the Mens meetings, and ſo be encouraged by us whoſe names are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſubſcirbed.</q>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Wilkinſon.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Henry Story.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Richard Stephenſon.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Henry Garner.</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:64952:58"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <p>THE laſt part of my preſent buſineſs is in ſomething by way of tender Counſel, and Brotherly advice unto all Friends of truth, both here and alſo beyond Seas, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That which will render you in a true Capacity in your ſeveral ſtations, to be a good ſavour in your places before the Lord, and Inſtrumental in his Bleſſed Hand, to be ſerviceable in advancing this great and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Work of the univerſal Reſtoration of the Sons and Daughters of men; is, as you are kept in the continual daily ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of your Spirits to the Leadings of that holy pure power of Almighty God, who hath called you unto a high and Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable vocation; For that hath been as well the ground of our preſervation in a right ſtate and good condition, as the alone founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the infinite loving kindneſs and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation of the tender Care of our heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father towards us, till this moment of time,</p>
               <p>And becauſe of the want of this holy ſubjection, in the particulars of thoſe who have been convinced of the bleſſed Truth, and publickly have appeared for it; but having gone from the life of it in themſelves,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:64952:58"/>and becauſe that they have not kept in the Conſtant dependency on the Lord, in the day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſelf-denyal, and in the Croſs to their own wills, and ſo have not abode in the lowlike, humble, meek and quiet peaceable Spirit of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> therefore is it that a <hi>diſorderly, treacherous, looſe, libertine, reaching, high, perverſe Spirit</hi> hath entered into them, and hath ſo far prevailed upon them, as to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence them thus to appear in ſuch an abuſive, heady, Croſs, oppoſite, willful and ſtubborn mind; that they become like thoſe mentioned in <hi>Jude, likewiſe</hi> alſo ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Theſe filthy dreamers</hi> (mark well the ſayings they are ſo appoſite to illuſtrate and clearly demonſtrate the very Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of theſe Apoſtates, <hi>defile the fleſh, deſpiſe dominion, and ſpeake evil of dignities, and of thoſe things which they know not; and what they know naturally as bruit Beaſts, in thoſe things they corrupt themſelves: Wo unto them, for they have gone in the way of</hi> Cain, <hi>and periſhed in the gain-ſaying of</hi> Core; <hi>theſe are Spots in your feaſts of Charity, feeding themſelves without fear, Clouds with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out water, Carried about with Winds; Trees, whoſe fruit withereth, twice dead plucked up by the roots; raging waves of the Sea, foam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out their own ſhame; wandering ſtarrs, to whom is reſerved the blackneſs of darkneſs
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:64952:59"/>for ever: But beloved, Remember ye th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> words which were ſpoken before by the Apoſtle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: How that they told you, there ſhould be Mockers in the laſt time, who ſhould walk after their own ungodly luſts,</hi> (and at laſt very evidently concludes, demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrating what perſons theſe are, as a ſignal mark to know them by) <hi>Theſe be they that SEPARATE themſelves, ſenſual, having not the Spirit.</hi> And Obſerve further how the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> deſcribes them more fully, for when they ſpeak great ſwelling words of vanity, they allure through the luſts of the fleſh, through much wantonneſs. While they promiſe them liberty, they themſelves are ſervants of corruption: For it had been better for them not to have known the way of righteouſneſs, than after they had known it to turn from the holy Commandment de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered unto them; but 'tis happened accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the true Proverb, <hi>the Dog hath turned to his own vomit again; and the ſow that was waſhed to her wallowing in the mire,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.</p>
               <p>Every one of theſe paſſages are ſo Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondent with, and agreeable to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices and wayes of this dividing oppoſite party, who have ſeperated themſelves from our bleſſed unity, Firſt as with reſpect to the good Spirit of God in their own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, and next (which of neceſſity and ſo
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:64952:59"/>naturally follows) as to fellowſhip, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and Communion with his People, and methinks one neer parallel, and a more cloſe compariſon could not be drawn as to every circumſtance betwixt thoſe in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles time, and thoſe in ours; it is ſo apparent that people of ſmall underſtanding may rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily obſerve the ſame.</p>
               <p>And its my firm Faith, and certain per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, that as on the one hand they are daily diſcovering their own ſhame, by their uncivil defamations abominable lyes and malicious ſuggeſtions, ſo on the otherhand ſhall their folly thereby be the more laid op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en: For as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> withſtood <hi>Moſes,</hi> So do theſe alſo reſiſt the Truth; but ſaith he, they ſhall<note place="margin">n="*" <hi>Obſ.</hi> In Gods appointed time all the reſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ers and Rebellers are ſtopped in their envy and malice againſt his People.</note> proceed no further; why ſo? the reaſon is clear as followes; for their folly ſhall be made manyfeſt (to whom? not only to a few, or a little rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant who from that inward ſenſe and true diſcerning, the Lord hath indewed them with, do ſee and have ſeen when firſt they began their wicked work of ſeparation, and before it was ſo notorious as it is now; but) unto all men as theirs was</p>
               <p>Now to return unto that which was moſt weighty in my view (having made ſome
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:64952:60"/>little digreſſion) ſeeing it hath thus ſadly befallen ſuch who have not kept their habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Truth, by reaſon of their woful departure from that due conſtant ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Spirits thereunto, having alſo the advantage of obſerving the Rock they have ſplit upon, and as this <hi>F. B.</hi> ſaies in his word of advice to the <hi>Pennſylvanians</hi> in his laſt Chap. ſuch a ſlender pitiful dry one as it is, and indeed I think better could not be well expected from him; for as I remember the ſubſtance of what he ſaies that's worth obſerving, much like to the dead pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, ſtrain, <hi>keep the Scripture in eſteem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, &amp;c.</hi> But never ſo much as a ſyllable of the antient Principle of Truth, <hi>viz.</hi> To mind the light of Chriſt) you may perceive what hath been one Impediment to the increaſe of love and Charity, which Bleſſed be the Lord God of Eternal Glory, plentifully abounds amongſt Friends in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Ireland</hi> &amp; other places, where this op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite dividing party hath not gain'd any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt among them, and ſo in moſt Counties of this Nation of <hi>England,</hi> where it hath not prevailed, there is great amity, bleſſed unity, ſweet concord, Peace &amp; Heavenly harmony, daily increaſes amongſt them; O Bleſſings and glory and Honour unto the Lord our God for ever for the ſame!</p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:64952:60"/>
               <p>Therefore my tender Counſel and brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly advice, in the love of our Lord Jeſus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you all is, be very Careful, that at all times, above all things whatſoever, and on all occaſions you may be found in that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Reverend ſubjection of your Spirits, to the bleſſed Divine power of the living God, that hath reached unto you, and by which you are Called to be his holy pure People, and then in this holy frame I do right well know ſhall you be kept neer unto and in unity with himſelf, and in concord and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip one with another, in the unity of his Spirit, and in the bond of peace, bundled up in the bundle of everlaſting Life, and ſo there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſhall you be preſerved from that rend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, tearing, and devouring Spirit; and the ſame God of bleſſings, who as he hath gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly attended you here in your various exerciſes, will alſo favourably accompany, and be preſent with you (his faithful, honeſt right-hearted ones) in all your ſeveral ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices for the advancement of his glorious work, even the Salvation of Souls, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion of the pure name, and the exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the glorious fame of holy Jeſus amongſt the Heathen and all the World over.</p>
               <p>And our Confidence is, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the great fury and wrath of the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:64952:61"/>Devil, the implacable malice and envy of his curſed agents, againſt the Lord &amp; his faithful Children, yet I am fully perſwaded Truth &amp; innocency ſhall over all prevail, as <hi>John</hi> ſaw, and ſaid <hi>behold a white horſe, and he that, ſate on him had a bow, and a Crown was given unto him, and he went Conquering and to Conquer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So I recommend you all to the ſaving Word of Gods Grace, that by it you may be guided, and under the ſafe conduct there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, preſerved to the End of all thoſe vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Changes, Tryals and troubles here; that you may finiſh your time, and teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and lay down your heads in peace, and in the cloſe of all return to your God, and my God, the Father of Spirits, from whence we came, &amp; with all the Heavenly Hoſt Laud and Extol his holy worthy Name, with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Songs of pure thankſgivings, and living praiſes, and ſo receive the product of all your labours, and excerciſes in the Lord, even the immortal Crown of eternal Glory and perpetual Renown; is the ſincere ſupplication of my Soul for you all, as for my ſelf, and who earneſtly prayes for the eſtabliſhment &amp; preſervation of all the Lords people upon the everlaſting Rock, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable Foundation, againſt which the Gates of Hell cannot prevail.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:64952:61"/>
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>AND now <hi>Francis Bugg</hi> I think I have done with thy book and ſpent more time then I Judge it either deſerved, or I deſigned in anſwer thereunto, and indeed never expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have been concerned with thee or any upon this Account, in publick eſpecially, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing altogether a Stranger, to &amp; unacquainted with thee, and therefore aſſure thy ſelf what I have written or may yet ſay unto thee, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of thy Adherents, is not from any Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, Heat or Prejudice, but really from that good-will, true tender love, and earneſt deſire which the Lord hath begot in my ſoul for the eternal welfare and happineſs of all the Sons and Daughters of Men, but more ſingularly for the reſtoration of ſuch whom God in any meaſure hath viſited with his Glorious Bleſſed Day, and reached unto by his everlaſting pure power, and thereby has tendered their Spirits, and broken their Hearts, and given, unto them a feeling and ſence of that Precious divine life, the conſtant enjoyment of which is above, and beyond all what this fading tranſitory World can afford.</p>
               <p>But what ſhall I ſay unto thee <hi>Francis
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:64952:62"/>Bugg,</hi> alas! how haſt thou betrayed thy great weakneſs, folly and envy? had it not been farr better for thee, thou hadſt never ſet Pen to Paper, in bringing forth ſuch a wicked. piece of work? haſt thou not clearly evinced there how aptly thy name anſwers to thy crooked perverſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and thy devliſh venomous diſpoſition, the enemy hath wrought in thee; for thou haſt done what thou could to wound, hurt and ſpoil, not only the good name and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of particular perſons; but haſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured with all thy ſtrength and poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to bring a laſh and blur upon many thouſands of faithfull Friends; howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, all thy Malicious ſmitings in the dark, and thy open notorious abuſes, and ſcandalous reflections will be in vain and return as a weighty load upon thy own head; for I know that the Innocency and uprightneſs of the one, with the honeſt cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect converſation of the other, will out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, confute and diſprove all thine, and the reſt of that helliſh Combination, your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged callumnies, and lying ſtories: and all your malicious inſinuations, and falſe ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions ſhall but redown to your own utter ruine, and everlaſting ſhame, perpetual de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famation, and eternal Confuſion, if you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent not, but ſtoutly perſevere, and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:64952:62"/>continue in this wilfull wicked work of oppoſition to, and ſeparation from the Lord and his People; and be of ſuch who have ſold themſelves to do wickedly, and ſo devoted to the Devils ſervice, to be his Vaſſals, Slaves and ſubjects. Oh! for ſhame, for ſhame, that ever it ſhould thus befall any who have made profeſſion of Gods Truth, and confeſſion alſo to the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thereof through many ſufferings and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and yet to become the abſolute great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt enemy to the Profeſſion and Progreſs of it; which I am perſwaded had more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſhined, and that more univerſally in the Nations, had not theſe Clouds of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, and ſeparation, looſneſs indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency and diſhoneſt converſation of many convinced of, and who have appeared for the ſame, come over to Ecclipſe the Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of this glorious day; but I know in due time the Sun of Righteouſneſs will ſo ariſe, and ſhine in that brightneſs and Glory, as that all theſe Miſts and Clouds, ſhall be diſpelled and ſcattered.</p>
               <p>And therefore this is that which is weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty upon my ſpirit in the Powerfull Name, of the Dreadfull God of Heaven and Earth, to warn you all to ceaſe from the evil of your doings, and O return, return, ſo long as it may pleaſe the Lord to ſtrive in you by his
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:64952:63"/>Holy gentle ſpirit, and bow every one to his righteous Judgments in your hearts to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy that wicked, perve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe oppoſing and ſeparating Spirit that's prevailed upon you; and remember what the Apoſtle ſaid, that is very weighty; For if God ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not the Angels that Sinned, but caſt them down to Hell and delivered them into Chains of Darkneſs; and ſpared not the old World, and turned the Cities of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorah,</hi> into Aſhes: and in his Exhortation to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> 10, 25. Says, <hi>Not forſaking the aſſembling of our ſelves together, as the manner of ſome is.</hi> (For ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve well what follows; Oh! how near and cloſe a Sentence is it) IF WE SIN WIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FULLY, <hi>after that we have received the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth, there remaineth no more Sacrifice for Sins, but a certain fearfull look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for of Judgment, and fiery Indignation which ſhall devour the adverſaries.</hi> Oh! dread fear, and ſtand in awe of the living Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, who is a conſuming fire to all the workers of iniquity, and who knoweth how to deliver the Godly out of Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to reſerve the unjuſt unto the day of Judgment; but chiefly them that walk after the fleſh, in the luſt of uncleanneſs, and diſpiſe Government; who are Preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſelf-will'd, they are not affraid to ſpeak evil of Dignities, (mark theſe ſayings.)</p>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:64952:63"/>
               <p>And let me tell you plainly, that for all your fair ſpecious pretences, Plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Eloquent Orations, ſmooth ſpeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, (cunningly contrived) your great and high Notions, glorious-like appearances, and Myſterious Transformations, may be as an Angel of light; or like unto a lamb covered with a profeſſion of Truth it ſelf and Preach up the words and Principles there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in the manly part and with the Wiſdom from below (thats your beloved darling) endeavours thereby to catch the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate itching part of ſimple People, and ſuch as are but young, raw, and unſettled in their minds; For all this know as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and which I am conſtrained in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fear of God to forwarn you off, You that are the workers of iniquity, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you may cover and hide your ſelves for a time <hi>from the Eye of Mortals, if you dye as thus you have lived, in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Work of</hi> Truth, in ſeparation <hi>from the Lord and his People,</hi> you (I ſay) ſhall be eternally excluded, and forever ſhut out from entering into the Pure ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Kingdom of Eternal Glory, reſt and Felicity; and the Lord Jeſus will no more acknowledge you, than he did thoſe, that though you (as they did) Cry, <hi>Lord, Lord, have we not Eaten and Drunken in thy
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:64952:64"/>preſence? have we not Propheſied in thy Name, and caſt out Devils, and done ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wonderfull works,</hi> (yet you ſhall meet with the ſame dreadfull Sentence) <hi>depart from me, I know you not, (for all your fair Plea) ye workers of iniquity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore this is a ſeaſonable warning to all you gain-ſayers, who are in the work of <hi>Corah,</hi> in the Devils work of Diviſion, oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of, tearing, rending and devouring, of diſorder and confuſion, and innovation, who are become mockers, ſcoffers and abuſers of the Lords work, and his Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent People, and that in a higher Degree than any of your former Predeceſſors; if you come not ſadly to mourn, deeply to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for, and unfeignedly to repent of the ſame, a moſt terrible heavy ſtroke and dreadfull cup of weighty <hi>vengeance</hi> ſhall be your Portion from the terrible hand of the mighty Pure God of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, the juſt Judg of Heaven and Earth, who ſhall reward every man according to his works.</p>
               <p>This from the Lord I lay before you, receive or reject it as you pleaſe, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I ſhall enjoy Peace with him in clearing my Conſcience to you and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging my Duty before him, and ſo ſhall be clear of your Blood; who ſincerely
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:64952:64"/>wiſheth, and earneſtly Prayeth for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of backſliders, and Reſtoration of all ſuch whoſe gracious day of Viſitation is not quite expired.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>By one that heartily prays for the daily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the Peace of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and the proſperity of</hi> Sion, <hi>and for the Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Holy</hi> Jeſus <hi>over all, throughout all the Earth. R. Sandilands.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:64952:65"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>FRANCIS BUGG,</hi> I deſire to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſe thee, that what I have now wrote in Anſwer to thy <hi>Book</hi> was in the <hi>Firſt</hi> place, with a regard to the clearing of my Conſcience inthe ſight of God, as a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony againſt. Malicious Oppoſers, and crued Hard-hearted Apoſtates; and in the <hi>Second</hi> place, it was with a true deſire, and real intent of mind, for thine and others good, if perhaps thou maiſt be thereby perſwaded of the evil of thy doings, repent thereof, and ſo obtain Mercy from the God of all Mercy, whom thou haſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly provoked to wrath againſt thee, by the many abuſive ſlanders and unchriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Calumnies, reproaching his holy Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Heritage: But in Caſe I ſhould not be anſwered therein, and thou rather prove more obſtinate perverſe and peeviſh againſt me, and the Lords people, and ſo ſhould
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:64952:65"/>take occaſion by this to bring forth and Publiſh to the World more groſs lyes, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent and ridiculous ſtories, or ſuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to thy forme: I do not intend to take much notice thereof, or ſpend my time ſo as to enter into a liſt of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie with thee; For as I ſaid alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, it was farr beyond my expectation e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to have been Concerned with thee, or any of thy party on this ſcore in theſe things, where there is little or no ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction found, eſpecially when we have to do with Croſs, heady and unreaſonable brutiſh Perſons: — And ſo farr now as I have cleared my Conſcience, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged my Duty, I ſhall enjoy Peace with my God, and reſt ſatisfied, being ſingly given up to follow him, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to perform that Service he hath allotted for me in my generation, and which as moſt proper for me to attend in that ſtation he ſhall place me; though I ſhould never ſet Pen to peaper, or thus Publicly appear again in theſe comfortleſs Contentions, and endleſs debates; for I
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:64952:66"/>do well underſtand in my ſmall meaſure, wherein the true Victory is obtained, and which I know cannot be by all the bluſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Noiſes and Clamours of wrong rambling and bragging Spirits detained from ſuch who are kept in a meek, quiet harmleſs and Innocent mind, whoſe Souls are poſſeſſed in Patience, and whoſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations are preſerved in that vertuous Bleſſed truth, in which alone is the true overcoming experienced; <hi>Everlaſting Glory to God on High.</hi> Amen, ſaith my Soul.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:64952:66"/>
            <head>ANOTHER <hi>INGREDIENT</hi> Againſt The <hi>Venom</hi> in <hi>E. B's.</hi> Book,</head>
            <p>F. BUGG abetting <hi>W. R.</hi> &amp;c. Like a Conceited man, Entitles his Book, to the Primitive Diſcipline, but Handles it not, but names <hi>Evagrius,</hi> and New Sirnames him <hi>Scholaſticus,</hi> as if it were to get himſelf thereby the opinion of a Schollar. And Dedicates his Book to his Honoured Friend, <hi>H. N.</hi> Kt. as writ many years ſince; as if he Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Antiquity, arguing from it, <hi>p.</hi> 7. If ſo, let him hear the many Authors following, many Ages Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enter, diſclam the later Author's Error, which is alſo his Author's, which bears its own Evidence of its ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Age with it, The <hi>Dutch</hi> Wars, which it mentions. Into whoſe Errors he leads his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Friend (as for his part) and his Readers, to whom he commends his Book to be read, after the Scriptures, and <hi>Ri. Hub.</hi> and F. <hi>H s.</hi> works (<hi>p.</hi> 215) without any exception, caution, praemunition, or anuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in his Epiſile, Preface or Margin; but owns his judgment as his own in this sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.<note place="margin">Praef to the <hi>2d.</hi> part</note> Now Conſcience is the Subject of the poſition that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is free, and is not that the Subject of the Book?
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:64952:67"/>In the beginning whereof he makes the light therein in ſome at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt, onely Natural, and not Divine Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally, in all men, Contrary to the Scriptures.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 1, 9.</note> And makes Conſcience, (at leaſt in ſome) a reflect Act of the Soul, Whereas the Scripture ſaith, <hi>the Conſcience alſo witneſſeth with them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2, 15.</note> 
               <hi>and thoughts between themſelves, accuſe or excuſe one another</hi> (Dialogue wiſe) then there muſt needs be two.<note place="margin">Diologiſmos</note>
            </p>
            <p>And the word Conſcience ſeemes to be uſed, as it were in the <hi>Concrete;</hi> as they term it, that which exerciſes,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1, 4. <hi>Jam.</hi> 3, 4.</note> of God; that which is exerciſed, of man; as Nature Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing, the Creator. Naturized the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture And <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelf though a main man for the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Doctrin, inclines to the Divinity of the light in men Univerſally, though a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſhy of ſpeaking more poſitively, for fear of abuſe by Phanaticks (as he calls them.) But to go higher to thoſe Fathers, as <hi>Clemens Alex. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> M. and other, cited already by our Friends ss by <hi>Wm. Pen G. Keith</hi> and others of our Friends I hope I may have leave (without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection.<note place="margin">n="*" And let not <hi>F. B.</hi> ſwel, as raiſing all the duſt, becauſe on thewheel. For tis to the Reader I bring them, whom he ſeeks to pervert &amp; proſelyte, as <hi>Simon</hi> did the Deputy, &amp; make worſe than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. <hi>Mat. 13. Acts, 13.</hi>
               </note>) on this occaſion to add ſome other writers I not known or remember, have yet obſerved by others, to ſhew ourjudgment agrees with the ancients, though many of late years call it a new light &amp; ſome no mean men, as <hi>W Prin,</hi> though it may ſeem ſtrange that perjudice ſhould ſo blind ſuch a great Antiqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:64952:67"/>
               <hi>John Selden,</hi> the greater, if not the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt of late times is not ſo blinded, but that he both ſees and approves the general acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of the Learned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the year 1400. that the light in the Soul of man Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally is Divine.<note place="margin">De jure Naturali &amp; Gent. <hi>lib. 1,</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> As firſt, The <hi>Gentiles,</hi> in whom <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, <hi>that which may be known of God is manifeſt.</hi> Epicharmus ſays, <hi>mans reaſon ſprung from God</hi> (which is agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to what <hi>Paul</hi> alledges out of <hi>Aratus</hi>) which reaſon muſt be underſtood of the Divine Reaſon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 17.28.</note> as <hi>Juſtine Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, Irenaeus,</hi> and others underſtand it,<note place="margin">Logos theos.</note> 
               <hi>Antoninus Emp ſays,</hi> the underſtanding agent is that which God hath given to every one for a Guide, &amp; of the Divine Nature. So <hi>Plato, Priſcianus Lydus, Alexander Aphroduſaeus, Marinus Neopolitanus, Ariſtotle, Themi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="*" Thought to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Moſes</hi> time.</note> The Author of <hi>Piman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Hermes,</hi> ſpeaking of Divine Preaching, without which men are Ignorant for what they are made, and whereby. The Antient <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſay, that the underſtanding that acts is God <hi>(and in their later Diſcipline, an intermediate Miniſter)</hi> as appears by <hi>Maimonides,</hi> citing their Doctors;<note place="margin">Shechinah. ruahh.</note> and that not onely for gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral principles of good and evil; but alſo for particulars, what they are, the Concluſions and propoſitions to be ſhewen perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually So the <hi>Arabians Avicenno, Avorroes, Arga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zel, &amp;c.</hi> ſay, That the underſtanding that acts is a thing ſeparate, by Divine Ordination, (though they agree not of its degree.) And that it is not humane form; nor a part of it, but ſomething more Divine.
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:64952:68"/>More of the Heathen &amp; <hi>Arabians John Philoponus</hi> hath,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>l. 3.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi> de an. <hi>l. 2,</hi> de Intel ag.</note> and <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus Magnus, Bonaventure, Zabarella,</hi> and others. The contrary opinion (That <hi>F. Bugg's</hi> Firſt part owns, his Second diſowns not that I find) was coming in, or growing on about 400 years ſince.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1250.</note> And therefore oppoſed by the Univerſities of <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Paris,</hi> and the Chief in them in thoſe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mes, as <hi>Robt.</hi> of <hi>Lincoln. W Avern</hi> of <hi>Paris. Adam</hi> de <hi>Mariſco, &amp;c. R. Bacon, M. S.</hi> to <hi>P. Clem.</hi> 4. c. 28. Cited at large by <hi>J. Selden</hi> oppoſes the Modern that ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1290.</note> 
               <hi>The Agent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telect was part of the Soul.</hi> All the Ancients <hi>(ſaith he) till our times, have ſaid it is God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zab. <hi>de mente agente.</hi> c 13. Scalig. <hi>exerc.</hi> 307. § 30. Bodin. <hi>Theat. nat.</hi> lib. 4.</note> The Ancient Tenet is reſumed of late by ſome Famous Learned men; as <hi>Zabarella, Cardan, Bodin,</hi> and others in <hi>Licetus.</hi> And ſeeing <hi>F. B</hi> ſeemes to have ſome reſpect for lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ving his Book a <hi>Latin</hi> title, and citing in <hi>Latin</hi> (with <hi>W. R</hi>) <hi>B Hooper's</hi> words, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tranſlating, and marring it with his Maſter, even in the firſt word. I may hope he may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear, ſo often Ironica ly to call me learned, learned, (as he has done though elſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>where unlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) for ſupplying his defect, or neglect at leaſt, in removing the ſtumbling blocks he has laid and left in the way of his Honoured Friend, and his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that he Dedicates and commends his Book to, whereof another is, (which is co-incident with, &amp; back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the former) making the Scriptures The rule Univerſal in every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular,<note place="margin">2. <hi>part</hi> p. 70,</note>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:64952:68"/>which contradict<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the former from being the Rule; and his former part, <hi>p.</hi> 58. Which makes that a difference between the Law and the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel. The Law writing down things particularly, not the Goſpel. And all the circumſtances in Scripture cannot now be recalled, unleſs the ſame Ages were brought about again (as the <hi>Platonics</hi> tell of their great year) as I have noted elſe where, from <hi>Muſculus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>God: can.</hi> l. 2. c. 11. § 12.</note> D. <hi>Mat. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liff,</hi> D. <hi>Bridges</hi> &amp; now lately D. <hi>Beveridge,</hi> (all Proteſtant writers) That there s no certainty of the perpetual Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church eſtabliſhed from the Apoſtles; that can be concluded from thoſe things that they are delivered to have done from their firſt Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but by little, and little, upon occaſion; and that the ſame Spirit breathed on the Apoſtles was Miniſtred to others. So he, whom I can follow no further. But muſt with Proteſtants, (<hi>Sadiel</hi> and others, I have cited elſewhere) return to an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate call after the Apoſtacy. And what method God will then uſe, he has not declared nor bound him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and man cannot do it. And <hi>F. Bugg</hi> deales fallaciouſly with me, in ſaying I do ſo with <hi>W. Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal,</hi> wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as I cite him and others not for particular ſervice, but general. <hi>F B.</hi> reaſons from ſervice in general, to particular ſervice. As he deals with the Scriptures, which muſt have a particular direction, ſuiting Circumſtances, from the <hi>adae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Canon.</hi>
               </note> or ſufficient Rule in the new creature, which reaches all truth, even perticulars, not onely General Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, but alſo aſſumptions, and concluſions as is ſaid
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:64952:69"/>afore (It is a Maxim or Rule,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>D.</hi> Andrews on Command.</note> that it is a point of greateſt power to reach the moſt remote.) And this Rule we have need of, and at hand at every inſtant * <hi>Fr. Bugg</hi> may find in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, this General. If the Son makes you free <hi>ye ſhall be free indeed,</hi> John 18.38. But where finds he his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption. (rather preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?) The Son makes <hi>F. B. free.</hi> (<hi>And therefore</hi> F. B. <hi>is free indeed.</hi>) Does he find this particular freedom in Scripture, tis well if he come to find it writen in his Heart? I am ſure he is not in the way of it, in this his dark way ward work, of bondage to the Spirit, tho' Liberty to the Fleſh. If he grant, not to perſons, times and other circumſtances, Can he find there the Meeting to be at <hi>Hadenham,</hi> in <hi>Ely,</hi> or once a quarter, month, week at ſuch an hour, and ſo long, &amp;c. Seeing the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Paul at</hi> Troas, <hi>abode</hi> 7. <hi>days,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 20.6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>broke Bread on Firſt day, continued till midnight, &amp;c?</hi> I have reaſon to ask him this queſtion; ſeeing he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the like of <hi>G. F.</hi> (about womens meetings) who held profeſſors to their Rule, as I do <hi>F B.</hi> Which meetings, <hi>J S.</hi> and <hi>J. W</hi> own'd in Cities,<note place="margin">4th <hi>p p.</hi> 38.</note> own'd by <hi>W. R.</hi> Or, will <hi>F. B.</hi> demand the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of having no Meeting, becauſe all Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in Scripture cannot be recalled. That is the Liberty that ſpirit would lead to, <hi>Libertiniſm, Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriſm, diſorderly, walking.</hi> But, do but conſider<note place="margin">n="†" See <hi>Oecolampadi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> and <hi>Junius,</hi> on <hi>Ezek. 2, 3</hi> of ſilent waiting, the General Calling; and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular inſtitution the particular calling.</note>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:64952:69"/>what a vaſt Chaſm and gulph this empty conceit void of form fixes betwixt his 2 parts; which this Son of <hi>Anak</hi> in his own Eyes ſeems to beſtride to make a co-herence. In his firſt part, indeed he makes a notable Defence with Reaſons, and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies againſt outward force as improper, une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual and inſufficient to urge and accompliſh matters pertaining to inward concerns: But yet gives away his Cauſe by leaving a weak place to let in the <hi>perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor</hi> to lay all waſte, by granting him a power to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell to things of a mixt Nature, and not purely Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural, but partly Moral, as hearing; But not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Sacraments; which, by his leave, is more groſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mixt than hearing, which he makes under the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates verge, as Moral. But Eating and Drinking, is Natural; and more ſtrictly ſo. Therefore if the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, much more this. If that which belongs to Morality, honeſty, &amp;c. Much more that which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to Sub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ty, Temperance, &amp;c. If compell Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to be waſh'd, and after ever to lend their Ears to attend to the mouths of whom he pleaſes; ſure he may compell them to let their mouths take Bread and Wine, or a Wafer-cake, from their hands. And thinks he yet their minds free enough; and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty enough for their Conſciences? Nay, the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits know better the effects of Education and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, and the laſting ſavour of the Liquor pour'd in at the Ears of the tender, and how the Eyes affect the Heart.:<note place="margin">J. Fox p. <hi>596.</hi>
               </note> Stands his liberty amidſt all their gaudys. <hi>Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pot,</hi> the Martyr tells them another tale, that think they have liberty to go to their places of worſhip. So that in his firſt part there's a great ſhortneſs for Liberty in Religion, and ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rciſe of a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:64952:70"/>towards God; which ſhould extend to things Natural &amp; Moral in themſelves; but with reſpect to Supernaturals, otherwiſe it limits our Service &amp; Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God after ſuch a manner as we conceivemoſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to him, to which outward violence is inef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual, to convince and render acceptable. Here he puts and leave another great block, or deep ditch in the way of his Honoured Pation and Reader, not at all heeded or not a ſtraw regarded or ſounded by this heedleſs, heady ſhallow Latiniſt and diſputer for liberty, but Patron of licenciouſneſs, conceiting himſelf Manager of the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Aſſociation, and Treater for a Ceſſation, though eager urger of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and Confuſion, to race out order in Church Affairs. For now mark, From this <hi>inadae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate</hi> inſufficient, imperfect and unſound Subject, or <hi>antecedent</hi> of his Firſt part, <hi>de Chriſtiana libertate,</hi> what a towering contradictory conſequence he makes i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his ſecond part, <hi>de Chriſtiana libertate:</hi> And on his inconſequent feet of Iron and Clay would eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh a <hi>Golden Babyloniſh Liberty, paramount over Church cenſure, which his Antecedent will not bear; which allows Church cenſure,</hi> pag. 138. Read him there at large.</p>
            <p>For his Conſequence in his two parts if any at all muſt needs be this, <hi>viz. Becauſe the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate by Natural and Moral power can onely compel Conſcience (which he cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s a reflect Act of the Soul) to mixt Moral Actions, as to hear, but not to ſuch as are purely Supernatural, as to receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as being onely Subject to Church-cenſure, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Spiritual nature, and not Subject to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward force.</hi> (The Subject or Argument in his firſt part, which he owns to be his Judgment in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:64952:70"/>to his ſecond part) Therefore the Church by the Spirit of Chriſt, may not exhort, nay not diſown any unſound Principle or practice in its mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, tending to Lic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iouſneſs or Scandal, and declare they have no unity with it, nor with them in it, leſt they be more Compulſive than the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate that impoſes Worſhip by outward violence &amp; force, (which is the conſequence in his ſecond part,) The Magiſtrates cannot compell, outwardly with carnal Therefore not the Miniſter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, with Spiritual weapons,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 14, 23. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4 2.</note> contrary to Scripture, and his firſt part allowing Spiritual cenſures. May the Magiſtrate compel to hear, and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter not be ſuffered to ſpeake, unleſs it be what plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes every hearer? Hear's Liberty of a bad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to the hearers; but no Liberty for a good Conſcience to the ſpeakers. This is the Liberty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed found in moſt places. As if he ſhould ſay The Cannon (as he writes and Prints it, and wrongs, mine) <hi>i.</hi> the great Gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, is not to be uſed againſt the Church,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.16.</note> but to ſhoot men into the Church. Therefore the Canon, <hi>i.</hi> the Rule of the new Creature is not to be uſed in the Church in admoniſhing them to walk by it, and reproving and diſowning them that do not, but are wilfull and diſorderly.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Richard Richardſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:64952:71"/>
            <lg>
               <l>HOW th' labouring man and <hi>Criſp</hi> and <hi>Bugg</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shrewdly at Women'<hi>s</hi> labours tug!</l>
               <l>Not meet apart; not ſpeak the leaſt</l>
               <l>Afore men; (if not after a Prieſt!)</l>
               <l>Not ope' their months, to ask men Nurſes</l>
               <l>Fo women! or to ope' their purſes!</l>
               <l>Should <hi>Rhapſodi</hi> one patch then lack,</l>
               <l>A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>et</hi> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itched on the back!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>HOW th' Serpent old creeps his old way;</l>
               <l>Ore' th' women ſeeks firſt to prevail;</l>
               <l>Meetings meet helps firſt to aſſay;</l>
               <l>That thereby mens hee may aſſail!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>HOW th' unleed vermin venemous thing,</l>
               <l>The wrigling crooked crawling beaſt,</l>
               <l>Seeks th' woman<hi>'s</hi> upright ſeed to ſting;</l>
               <l>Or th' heel thereof to hurt at leaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>THE Serpent<hi>'s</hi> ſeed<hi>'s</hi> a <hi>Cockatrice,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which fiery flying Dragon grows.</l>
               <l>Himſelf an outcaſt when he ſpyes,</l>
               <l>He floods of <hi>Venom</hi> at her throws.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>p. <hi>97. for</hi> (Rogers Team) <hi>read</hi> (Team Rogers)</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64952:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
